<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition of the hymne commonly called Benedictus with an ample &amp; comfortable application of the same, to our age and people. By A. Anderson preacher.</title>
            <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835988</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19257)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 165:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition of the hymne commonly called Benedictus with an ample &amp; comfortable application of the same, to our age and people. By A. Anderson preacher.</title>
                  <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 72, 71-77, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Middleton, for Raufe Newbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1574]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>The dedicatory epistle dated: 15. of January. 1573 [ecclesiastical calendar].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Benedictus Dominus Deus Israel --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:226:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:226:1"/>
            <p>An Expoſition <hi>of the Hymne commonly</hi> called <hi>Benedictus: <hi>with an ample &amp; comfortable</hi>
               </hi> application of the ſame, to <hi>our age and people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By A. Anderſon Preacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Stay prophane &amp; vain bablings, for they ſhall encreaſe vnto more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlines. <bibl>2. Timothe. 2.16.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>But if you haue bitter enuying and ſtrife in your harts, reioyce not, neither be liars againſt the truth. This wiſdom diſcendeth not from aboue, but is earthly, ſenſuall, and diueliſh. For where enuying and ſtrife is, there is ſedition, and all maner of euill woorkes.</p>
               <bibl>Iames. 3.14.15 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by</hi> Henry Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delton, <hi>for</hi> Raufe Newbery.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:226:2"/>
            <head>The booke to the Reader.</head>
            <l>To prayſe the Lord is my deſire,</l>
            <l>To helpe his Church all that I can:</l>
            <l>To quench if could, ſuch burning yre,</l>
            <l>As Satan late hath caſte in man:</l>
            <l>VVhile pen doth carpe at brothers ill,</l>
            <l>Sinne taketh reſt, the Church doth ſpill.</l>
            <l>For other ſtate ſome men do craue,</l>
            <l>And cut themſelues from this we haue,</l>
            <l>In hart they hate thy ſtate and life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>They ioy to ſee thee at ſuch ſtrife</l>
            <l>And they at eaſe: do by diſdaine</l>
            <l>Inuent all meanes t'encreaſe thy pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Their Pope and Maſſe they long to ſee,</l>
            <l>Our Chriſt, his law and vnitie</l>
            <l>They do blaſpheme, through our diſcent,</l>
            <l>In caſes new of gouernment:</l>
            <l>Thy brawle, their broyle would come to end,</l>
            <l>If ceaſe thou couldſt thus to contend.</l>
            <l>Ioyne hands in one, embrace remorce,</l>
            <l>To banish ſinne bend all thy force,</l>
            <l>Thy ſelfe reſtraine, Gods truth reſpect,</l>
            <l>His Church, and peace of his elect.</l>
            <l>Vouchſafe vs Lord thy Chriſt his grace,</l>
            <l>Our Queene thy ſprite, but ſinne deface.</l>
            <closer>Amen.
<signed>A.A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:226:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>To the right reuerend</hi> Father in God <hi>THOMAS</hi> by the <hi>mercifull prouidence of God, Bishop</hi> of <hi>Lincolne</hi> his good L: <hi>Anthony <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon Miniſter of the good Goſpel of</hi>
               </hi> God, wiſheth all health and peace, in Chriſt our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauiour.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth, that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> whatſoeuer thinges are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore time are written for our learning, which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence (reuerend father) as often as I do remember, by the hand leadeth mee deepely to conſider with reuerent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard what I read in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and vrgeth me by feruent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to craue of God, the geuer<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iac. 1.17.</note> of all good giftes, in Chriſt, the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures ſenſe, and the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Math. 13.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hidden treaſures therein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed. And ſo hath it pleaſed the lord
<pb facs="tcp:226:3"/> of life to open the windows of heauen, (his name bee euer praiſed) and from thence by his ſpirite, moſt familiarly to ſpeake vnto mee by his written word: So that to his great prayſe, and my endleſſe comfort I ſee that no iot of his Law is voyd of moſt excellent comfortes to the heart, that ſimply in integritie of ſoule ſeeketh to quench his thirſt in this fountaine of health, the Goſpell of God.</p>
            <p>In this word I find the knowledge of God &amp; Chriſt his ſonne, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his holy ſpirit shall in all his elect open their hartes, and write in them the true vnderſtanding of his lawes. Ezec. 36. The which moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent gift by the learned books, ſince the time of the Apoſtles, and penned trauels of ſundrie godly fathers in the Church, (aſwell before our times as in theſe our dayes) doth appeare to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now moſt florishing in the church
<pb facs="tcp:226:3"/> of God, his name be alwayes prayſed therefore.</p>
            <p>And wherefore did the Prophets by his ſpirite ſpeake? or Chriſt and his Apoſtles preach? or the godly Fathers before vs? or theſe our learned writers in this age? VVherefore I ſaye with hart, mouth, and penne, haue they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed? But to vtter the teſtimonie of gods gift, &amp; confeſſe his name to the people of the earth, to the life of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, &amp; the inexcuſe of the reprobate. So will the Lord haue his ſpirite euer reſiant in his Church, to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>To follow theſe Fathers as they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe Chriſt, I accompt it my part, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing for further example amongeſt the many worthy workes of our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters now, your L. profitable worke lately ſet forth, to the better taſt of Gods good wil, in his expreſſed word in the appoynted Leſſons at common
<pb facs="tcp:226:4"/> prayer. Of which worke I ceaſe to ſpeake further, and ſeeke to follow as I can ſuch good examples to the ende before touched. VVhat if my Mite be not much worth? Yet as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Lord of heauen, ſo shal it no doubt profite thither to his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and that is my whole deſire. Let the learned eares accept as in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior place this my ſmall coyne, yet good curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſiluer (I truſt) tried by the touch of truth, and geue him licence to paſſe, to the leſſe learned and poore countrey people, whoſe ſtate requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth yet mornings milke, not all able for ſolidate queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or deepe digeſted miſteries. Their ſoules are precious in the ſight of God: their liues ought to be deare in our conſciences: their wounded hartes require ſome ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne medicine of gentle digeſture, and quiet operation: yet ſo, that their ignorance &amp; weaknes may be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="tcp:226:4"/> which God for his mercies ſake in Chriſt, vouchſafe them richly in his loue. This is not the leaſt cauſe why I haue ſtirred vp the ſmall gift of God in me, to exerciſe the ſame vpon this Hymne vſed in and at the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer. Iudging, as by order through vſe the wordes are readie at the lippe to vouch the Prophetes ſpeech: So if their tender hartes had ſome helpe to open therto the hidden cauſe of ioye in that holy letter, no doubt (I ſay) the ſame of them shuld both with hart and mouth ioynd in one conſent of grateful harmonie, crie out the praiſes of the Lord in the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of the holy Ghoſt, which is the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph. 5.19.20.</note> ſong that deliteth only the muſical eares of Gods maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly al other chaunting notes and changing keys, ſeeme they neuer ſo pleaſant in the eares of men, are far eſtranged from the good like of god,
<pb facs="tcp:226:5"/> al if ſet vp in his houſe of prayer.<note place="margin">Eſay 29.13. Math. 15.8. Marc. 7.17.</note> This people worship me (ſaith God) with their lippes, but their hartes are farre from me. In vaine do they ſerue me. &amp;c. And albeit I cannot touch the ſtile worthie ſo high a matter, or ſet downe ſuch deepe doctrine as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the place requireth, or yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch ſuch the hidden treaſures as are here layd vp, or the finenes of this our age expecteth: yet, nay the leſſe, the wydowes Myte<note n="(b)" place="margin">Luc. 21.2.</note> is my boldninge comfort: And on the other part the ſorowfull lookes of the ſlothful Miſer to whom the Lordes Talent<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 26.24.</note> was imparted, maketh me afraid to que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch the ſpirit, or ſtay the firie word kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in my hart (if I may vſe Ieremies wordes) at this preſent.<note place="margin">Ier. 20.</note> But be it that I should blushe to preſent my ſimple ſkill, to the ſcanning of the wiſe and sharpned ſight of the loftie learned &amp; deepe Doctors of our time, knowing
<pb facs="tcp:226:5"/> that my owne weaknes, is to ſundrie of them knowne alſo inable to this ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ploit, in reſpect of infinit others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet I ioye at this refuge, my conſcience beareth me witnes tofore GOD and men, that the onely end and ſcope of this my pen is chiefely to promote Gods glory, then to vſe rightly my loned penie in dutifull ſort to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church of God, here in this our ſtate and Realme by his great mercie, firmely ſet vpon the foundation ſtone<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.11.</note> Chriſt Ieſus. This Ancker is to me a ſtaye, and frayeth all feare from me, ſo that I (as I can) ſeeke to helpe forwardes the Lords labours, though wants in me, do force the wish of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned frame, and eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t phraiſe to help my willing mind and godly purpoſe. But I accept with thankfulnes, that which God hath vouched ſafe to giue (being becauſe of my many ſinnes, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy of that in him I haue) I onely
<pb facs="tcp:226:6"/> deſire of God in Chriſt, that his ſpirit of truth may guide my ragged rowes and ſimple ſtile, and that the leſſe lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned (for whom chiefely I preſume theſe preſents) may ſomething here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with be profited.</p>
            <p>The matter that I exhibit to your L. is An Expoſition with an ample &amp; true applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that Hymne which by order of the conſtituted Lawes of England is now appoynted to be vſed at Morning prayer: which Hymne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly is called BENEDICTVS. Not at all purpoſed to controll, much leſſe to condemne the minds of ſome of our bretherne, whoſe Cenſure hath exiled his vſe at the Common praier: Or yet to lend my like to phantaſies luſt, where ſound warrant hath no place. And waighing with my ſelfe, that neither they may by their priuate power, or can with the quietnes of Gods Church in England, (which
<pb facs="tcp:226:6"/> ought neceſſarilie of all Chriſtians to be had in moſt regard) to take from her that and thoſe thinges which by Law she hath eſtablished. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more reuoluing my cogitations, that this Hymne (howeſoeuer of ſome it be diſliked to his appoynted vſe) is tho, a part of holy ſcripture. I thought it better (to that I could) to open ſome of the hidden treaſures layd vp in the ſame for the Church of God: then to feede ſome forren phantaſie, or to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute my pen in contending to pull downe that which may well enough ſtand, and nothing abate the beautie of Gods houſe.</p>
            <p>Yet do I not thinke this Hymne ſo neceſſarily ſet in the order of prayer, as without the ſame it were blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for that were more than friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: but becauſe the matter therin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained (indifferently looked into, and well weighed) doth enſtruct, comfort,
<pb facs="tcp:226:7"/> and alſo adminiſtreth light to our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſences, and vnderſtanding of Gods mercies, in his promiſed Chriſt to vs geuen, and long ſith commen in the Flesh, (which matter in time of prayer is expedient.) I can not yet learne or be of other minde, then that the ſaid Pſalme as it is appointed, is both tollerable and profitable to all godly heartes. And were theſe my weake labors worthy by their valor, to force the fauor of chriſtian frend, &amp; to refell the fury of Popish foe, to your good L. of right I ought to dedicate the ſame: not only becauſe you are my lerned godly Ordinary, who can with good iudgment, diſcerne the doctrine therin contained, if either ſounde or contrary, (that ſo in ſtead of milke the meate for babes, I powre not out poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to infect the well growne vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Chriſt, for that God graunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be farre from me:) but alſo for
<pb facs="tcp:226:7"/> that in reſpect that I should not loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but labor in the vineyard of the Lorde, your goodneſſe at the requeſt of the right honorable my ſinguler good L. and Maſter (as you know) did commit vnto me a ſpeciall flock with in your Dioceſe, to foſter vp in Chriſt their ſoules, which he hath purchaſed with his moſt bleſſed bloud. Let this little booke beare witneſſe of my dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent care (therfore my good L.) that I beare, both to the ſame my peculiar charge, amongſt whom, and of whoſe labors I reape my portion and liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, and to the whole church of God elſewhere, where theſe my low lines, with others godly woorkes, may fruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify by his holy grace and ſpirit, in the apt ſoyle of their poore harts, had they ſtore of godly teachers.</p>
            <p>Finally I beſeech your L. that my poore pen may paſſe the raging Seas of curious cenſure, vnder the harbor
<pb facs="tcp:226:8"/> of your protection: So shall it with much more quietnes arriue in the port of the poore mans hart, deſirous not to cauill, but to catch earneſt holde of ſuch plaine doctrine, as truly, though ſimply, teacheth him the way to life. This if I may of your good nature ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine, it will encourage me, the further aduenture of godly ſtudy in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures, if ſo it may pleaſe the almightie in his Sonne Chriſt, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a greater porcion of me, that I may ſtill bring foode into the church of God.</p>
            <p>The Lord God of mercy, loue, and peace, ſend to this our church, her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtrate our godly Queene, ſtate and people, the peace of Chriſt vnfainedly in our hartes for his names ſake, and to your L. encreaſe of godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, like zeale, and perfect ſtrength to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue with godly care, euer more and more profitable to his Church,
<pb facs="tcp:226:8"/> by the power of his ſpirite, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be euer yours, and you with all vs that inuocate truely the name of God, for euer his, in Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L. euer in Christ.</hi> A. Anderſon.</signed> 
               <dateline>From Medborne <date>this 15. of Ianuary. 1573.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:226:9"/>
            <head>The argument of the <hi>Propheticall Hymne</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe author of this ſong was the holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Prieſt of the Lord Zacharias,<note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> who had to wife Elizabeth the coſen of the vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gin Mary the mother of Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe old age the Lord by his Angell promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him of his ſaide wife a Sonne, and called his name Iohn, which Iohn the Lord had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the ſame Prophet, and fore runner of the Meſſiath that the prophetes Malachy and Eſay had propheſied to precede Chriſt. At the birth of this babe, Zacharie his toung was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly lowſed (which before for a ſeaſon was dumbe for his harde beliefes ſake,) and he with exceading ioy, then, in the ſight of all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, made and ſung this Song. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſraell &amp;c.</hi> In this hymne is commended vnto vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> (1) Firſt the conſtant truth of God to his beloued Church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> (2) Then his ineſtimable mercies powred vpon the ſame. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> (3) Thirdly the office of Iohn and of the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word: All which are more at large in the woorke following, amply ſet forth to gods glory, and thy profite.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:226:9"/>
            <head>¶ An expoſition of the Hymne commonly called <hi>Benedictus.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Luke. 1.68.</note> for he hath viſited &amp; redeemed his people.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy ghoſt more ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtly now then before, prouoketh &amp; forceth his Prophete <hi>Zacharie</hi> to ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forth his praiſe as in this Hymne is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: his harte béeing ſet downe in the Chaire of déepe conſideration of Gods mercie to <hi>Jſraell,</hi> beginneth wyth laude and prayſe to God for their and our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſraell,</hi> ſayth he, hée calleth God the God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> not becauſe he reigneth onely ouer Iſraell, for he is alſo the God<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 3.29. &amp; 15.12.</note> of all the Worlde, and in him ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:226:10"/> the Scripture ſhall the Gentilles truſt:<note place="margin">Eſa. 11.10</note> But becauſe he<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deut. 7.6.7 8.9.14.2.26 18. Exo. 19.5. 1. Pe. 2.9.</note> choſe them from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the nations, not for their worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but in his mercie, to be a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to him ſelfe,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Exo. 13.21. et 14.19.20 1. Sam 4.4</note> from heauen by his preſence he guided them: to them he gaue his<note n="(d)" place="margin">Re. 9.4</note> ſtatutes &amp; ordinances, his Prieſtes and Prophets, wyth them he made his ſpeciall couenant, and gaue vnto their Tribes the Sacramentes, ſeales of his faythfulneſſe: to them he promiſed, that of the kindred of Iſraell, he would rayſe vp his holy Child Ieſus, which ſhould be, and before all times was of the ſame our eternall God determined to be, the ſauiour of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Iſraelites. Theſe be the cauſes why he termeth him the God of Iſraell. <hi>Becauſe he hath viſited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed. &amp;c.</hi> Thrée principall cauſes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing forth ſuch prayſes, the Prophete here declareth: firſt that our God not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtanding that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſay. 59.2.3 Ier. 5.25. Eſai 5.18.</note> the ſinnes of his Church ſeperateth his preſence from her, and in ſtead thereof draweth his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon her, as it were with cordes, yet the malice of her ſinnes cannot break<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſ y. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the faythfulnes of him, her God. But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:226:10"/> according to his worde, by othe alſo war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.9. 2. Tim. 2.13 Ro. 3.3.</note> he would vouchſafe in her moſt miſerie, ſo louingly to viſit the ſame his Church and people. Secondly he viſiteth his choſen Church with ineſtimable loue, moued wyth compaſſion vpon the vewe of her great miſerie, who for her ſinnes was by his iuſtice Captiued into ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude (not onely to <hi>Caeſar</hi>) but alſo to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and ſo holden of him in thrall, that no way could ſhe auoyde Sathans force, or at the tribunall ſeat of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſcape the iuſt ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, neceſſarily following her wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as a méete merit to the ſame. At his appoynted time according to his good pleaſure, he wyth his<note n="(a" place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> apparant fauor, ſo viſiteth the ſame perplexed Church, that from her Captiuitie in ſinne, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans bondes, and alſo from the iuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his great wrath, he by his ſonne Chriſt hath perfectly raunſomed, &amp; ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemed her (not by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t force taking hir from her bondage, as erſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Exo. 14.30.</note> 
               <hi>Pharao</hi>) nor mouing the hartes of her Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, to pitie her miſerie, and fauor her deliuerance, (as ſomtime he<note n="(c)" place="margin">Nehe. 2. Eſay. 1.2.3.</note> did) when
<pb facs="tcp:226:11"/> ſhe was in <hi>Babilons</hi> captiuitie, but aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering his iuſtice wyth the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſay. 53.5.6 7.8.9. &amp;c. 1. Pet. 1.18.19.20.</note> bloud and death of his immaculate and iuſt ſonne Ieſus, hath payed there by the due price of her ſinne, and deliuerance from his wrath and from Sathans malice, to the end that ſhe ſo redéemed ſhould leade a<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tit. 2.12. 1. Pet. 2.24.</note> purchaſed life voyd of ſinne, and by his holy ſpirite<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ephe. 5.14.15.</note> redéeme hereafter ſuch ill time, as erſt they waſted with<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ephe. 4.19.22.</note> gréedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to iniquitie, and by newneſſe of life walke as children which in the dungeon of darknes haue ſéene ſo great light, that as by their former actions his holines was blaſphemed, ſo now by their good<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> woorkes his name may be glorified. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly when he ſayth <hi>He hath redemed his people,</hi> he ſturreth all Iſraell to a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that their gouernour and Lorde is no leſſe then the Lord God, who hath made all things that be, the<note n="(e)" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.15 Apo. 1.5. &amp; 17.14. &amp; 19 16.</note> Lord of Aungelles, of Men, and Deuilles, and hath al at his becke, ruleth al at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſtaieth the rage of<note n="(f)" place="margin">Eſay 11.5.6.7.8. Dan. 14.</note> Lyons, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth the innocencie of Doues, and the ſimplicitie of his beloued ſhéepe: As alſo that he is a viſiting God, doth not onely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:226:11"/>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Pro. 16.4.</note> create but dayly direct by gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from an hye, the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pro. 16.9.</note> ſteps &amp; rhodes of all thinges, and in his ielouſie ouer the<note n="(i(" place="margin">Pro. 16.5.</note> wicked for their crueltie to his people,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſay. 53. Eſa. 27.1 Ier. 14.10. Gene. 12.17 Ier. 44. Amos. 9.10</note> viſiteth their ſinnes wyth ſcourges, and wyth the ſworde of his plagues. But his people he in viſiting finding in them like corruption of nature, the mountains of ſinne, the lyke little regarde of dutie to God, and remorſe of themſelues, doth not wyth the wicked deſtroy them, but as a moſt mercifull Father (regarding for his names ſake, not their deſerued plague, but the enemies rage againſt them) doth acknowledge them for his, and from the ſhadow of death,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 6.16.23.24.</note> the Lyons denne, the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Dan. 3.8 25</note> burning Ouen, the manifolde capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities and fierie cheynes of ſinne (becauſe they are by his owne worke his people) he redéemeth them, and tranſlateth them into the kingdome of his deare ſonne our ſauing health Chriſt Ieſus. Now let vs (good readers) applie the wordes of this verſe to our ſelues, which not onely in the morning, but at all times of prayer, finding the lyke cauſes working in vs, we ought wyth ioyfull hartes to the
<pb facs="tcp:226:12"/> Lorde vnfainedly to ſay and ſing, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lorde. &amp;c.</hi> Firſt this Lorde and God belongeth to vs now as to Iſraell of olde. For as they were after the fleſhe the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham:</hi> So, many of them not hauing the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 4.13. et. 9.31.32.</note> fayth of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, loſt the promiſe to him and his ſéed, and we now are in<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 11.17.18 19. &amp;c.</note> their ſtéede grafted into Chriſt, by whoſe ſpirite and worde preached, we are made the children of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> not by birth in fleſhe, for we are of another ſtocke Gentilles, but by the gyft<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 3.7.29.</note> of fayth, whereby our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maketh vs the members of his ſon Chriſt, who is the true ſéede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> wyth the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Iſraellites. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as many as are the children of faith, may they, and ought they, as ſonnes of <hi>Abraham</hi> in déede, to ſing wyth thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes vnto God. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord. &amp;c.</hi> The viſitation of our Lord then had, and now continually of him vſed, chalengeth alwayes ioy of vs. For, in<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 101.8.</note> viſiting the wicked wyth his ſworde, he cutteth the occaſion of euill from his people. In viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his people with his rod, he deſerueth great prayſe, for to the ſame his people,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:226:12"/> whenſoeuer he ſendeth his Rodde to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their ſinnes,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 23.4</note> his ſtafe of diuine prouidence, is alſo by his mercie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth exhibited, to be to them a ſtaye of comfort and defence. All which moſt wiſely he guideth wyth his merciful ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, oftentims not taking from his ſeruants, the ſmarting ſalue of his correction, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the itching ſore of their iniquitie, by the power of his ſpirite be taken from them. As a moſt louing Father, he viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs, for in the middeſt of his anger he is euer mindful of his mercies.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſai. 54.4.1 6.7.8.</note> He ſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth vs but for a ſeaſon, but he conſumeth the wicked in his wrath, he<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 119 67 71. 1. Cor. 11.32</note> beateth vs to our good, to bring vs vnder his yoke But w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his viſiting plagues, he<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 2.9</note> brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in ſunder, and beateth into morſels, the children of iniquitie, for the which his holy workes ſake, we ought euer thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſay wyth harte and tongue to the Lorde our God. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord. &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly haue not wée manifeſt cauſe wyth <hi>Zachary</hi> dayly to prayſe God? when wyth him féeling our deſerued death rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to deuoure vs, and our ſinnes prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods iuſtice to condemne vs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb facs="tcp:226:13"/> captiuitie to impriſon vs in<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iud. 6. 2. Pet. 2.4.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall cheynes of darkeneſſe wyth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than) he by his ſpirite doth aſſure vs that we are his children,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 8.15.16.</note> and<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.18. Gal. 4.6.</note> enboldeneth vs, (not whiſperingly for feare bringing painefulneſſe: But to crye out wyth courage enriched wyth his loue) that he is our Father, and that his<note n="(d)" place="margin">Io. 3.16.</note> Chriſt is by his goodneſſe geuen to vs, and by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite hath he grafted vs into his Chriſt, as the braunches are into the true vine, by whoſe ſappe euen his ſayd ſpirite wée haue not onely our <hi>Arra,</hi> and<note n="(e)" place="margin">Eph. 1.13.14</note> earneſt penie of his aſſured couenant: But alſo are ſet ſo ſure into eternall lyfe, that it is impoſſible for ſinne, ſatan, fleſh, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo euer, to condemne vs. For it is our Lorde which hath redéemed vs his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and we are by<note n="f)" place="margin">Rom. 8.1</note> fayth grafted into him our Lorde: So that to vs can come no condemnation, nor any want of that which is good. Therefore agayne wyth the whole Church of God we moſt ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to ſay. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lorde God &amp;c. For he hath viſited and redeemed his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, note here that the Papiſtes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:226:13"/> in their Mattins vſing, or rather into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe bringing and chaunting this ſong did neuer a right as Zacharie the good Prieſt did, therewith praiſe the Lord, for they worſhipped him with lippes alone, without vnderſtanding the cauſes why: but he firſt waigheth the cauſe, before hée poureth out by waight the Lordes praiſe. His hart was wholy fraught with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued matter of ioy, they voyd thereof &amp; laden with terrible doubtfulneſſe, dare not preſume (ſay they) to boſt of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, which popiſh vice as it is their deuotion in their life, ſo it purchaſeth for them after death the dregges of Gods angrie Cup, as dreaming Dirgis, and reſtleſſe Maſſes, to purchace <hi>requiem,</hi> where none is to be had, and a neuer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing paye, till land and reuenewes wyll ſerue no more. And yet if eftſones of them it be aſked, neuer can it by them be aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, the ſoule the Lord viſiting hath redéemed: for then their poperie ſhould decay. But thankes be vnto God, who by his vnfallible truth in his writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word hath aſſured as many as beleue in him, of eternall life: yea and that preſently after,
<pb facs="tcp:226:14"/> and from the moment of naturall death: our Lord and redéemer ſo ſaying<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 11.25. &amp; 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>hee that beleeueth in me, ſhall not die for euer. &amp;c. but ſhall paſse from death to life.</hi> O ye Papiſtes learne to repent (which God if it be his good wil graunt you for Chriſtes ſake) and to perceiue with vs the cauſes why we bleſſe the Lord, for he hath erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp an horne of ſaluation in the houſe of his ſeruant <hi>Dauid,</hi> for the Church of true Iſraell, as this our good Prieſt and Prophet Zacharie ſpeaketh on this wiſe ſaying.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>2</label> And hath rayſed vp the horne of ſaluation vnto vs, in the houſe of his ſeruaunt Dauid.</q>
            <p>Albeit (ſayth the Prophet) that in the eyes of all men Iſrael, was caſt downe, his ſtrength worne out, and his light ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, his hope gone, and no glory left in the houſe of <hi>Dauid:</hi> yet do I now ſée thée O Lord, mindfull of thy former promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For in that thou haſt ſent my ſonne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:226:14"/> the Baptiſt, thy meſſenger, and enriched the wombe of the virgin with child, thou haſt aſſured vs of thy erected Chriſt in the Tabernacle of <hi>Dauid,</hi> which is to vs a moſt mightie ſaluation by thy ſpirit, in the mouth of the ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> promiſed ſaying. <hi>There will I make the horne of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to bud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.17 Iere. 23.6</note> 
               <hi>for I haue ordained a light for mine anoynted.</hi> And the time now, thou haſt reſpected to the ineſtimable comfort of thy Church, in which <hi>Herod</hi> and thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies haue periſhed (in ſhew) thy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> line, and haue vſurped his throne. As thou before time haſt promiſed, ſaying: <hi>Jn that day will I rayſe vp the Tabernacle of Dauid that is falne downe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 9.11. Acts. 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>and cloſe vp the breaches therof. And J will rayſe vp his ruines, and J will build it as in the dayes of olde.</hi> A horne he calleth Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſignificantly, thereby checking the pride of Sathan in his members, that ſéeke to deſtroy the kingdome of Iſraell, as alſo declaring that he ſhalbe of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to ouercome their ſtrength: yea and that his place and dignitie is no where els the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Lorde, who doth anoynt this Chriſt aboue his fellow Prieſtes &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:226:15"/> with the Horne of his Euerlaſting ſtrength for his people. Vnderſtand ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that this word <hi>Cornu</hi> a horne in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſometime ſignifieth<note n="(a)" place="margin">Dan. 7.7.24. 1. Sa. 16.1.</note> kingdom and princely power, as in <hi>Daniell</hi> and in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel.</hi> Sometime it is taken for ſtrength and great might, as in <hi>Daniel</hi> againe, and in the <hi>Pſalmist,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 75.10.</note> 
               <hi>All the hornes of the vngodly will J breake, but the hornes of the iust (ſaith he) ſhalbe exalted.</hi> The ſum of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophets wordes are, as if he had ſayd: To vs depriued of ſtrength, hope and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, by the mightie enemies of god in the world, the Lord in deſpite of them that throw vs downe to the duſt, hath erected in the midſt of them his promiſed Chriſt, which is to vs that beleue in him, <hi>a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie king, a ſtrong ſaluation.</hi> That, and the only ſauing health of God, giuen to al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that feare him, and call vppon his name. Yea, and that in the ſame linage and ſtocke which the mightie of the world are now in hand to deſtroy, euen in the houſe of his ſeruant <hi>Dauid.</hi> Since to vs this horne with his honour and ſtrength is erected, let vs conſider ſomething fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe the Prophets wordes. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:226:15"/> firſt note that in Chriſt alone, which is borne of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtocke, the virgin Mary, (not in the popiſh wheaten and coniured counterfet Chriſt,) hath the heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther placed our<note n="(a)" place="margin">Math. 17.</note> ſauing health and in no other: wherefore in him alone muſt wée repoſe our truſt, as in whom the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Col. 1.19. &amp; 2.9.</note> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Godhead and his whole fauour dwelleth corporally, and in whom alone<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 3.17. &amp; 17.5.</note> he reſteth with vs pleaſed, whoſe name is<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iere. 23.6.</note> the Lord our righteouſnes. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he is of God, ſet vp to be our ſaluation, therefor may we not els where ſéeke for health, of Man or Angell, neither feare any other power, for neither<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 8.38.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſinne, Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than, world, or Hell, can take our ſauing health from vs that reſt in him, nor ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from him &amp; his merites, thoſe which the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Io. 6.37.39 &amp; 16.22. &amp; 17.24.</note> father hath geuen to him. Thirdly the ſame horne that to the wicked is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and vgly,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Dan. 11.12.</note> deſtroying their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and tiranny, is to the faithfull the horne of their health in God, from the ſicknes of their ſinne. And alſo it is to them life into heauen, from and againſt the death in hel. As the ſame water which drowned the wicked of the world, neither
<pb facs="tcp:226:16"/> ſparing Shippe, Citie, Towne, or Caſtel, at the ſame inſtant caried the Arke of the obedient<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 6.7.8</note> 
               <hi>Noah</hi> and his familie from deſtruction. Yea, and as naturall death it ſelfe, is to the wicked, the doore to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fire: So is the ſame naturall death, by this our ſtrength Chriſt Ieſus (who hath ouercome death, and her ſting) to vs that rightly beleue in him,<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55.56.57. Heb. 2.14.</note> the paſſage to eternall ioye and bliſſe. Let the Papiſts therefore tremble at the preſence of this our ſtrength, for neither they<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat 16.18.</note> or the gates of hell, ſhall or can preuayle in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle againſt vs, becauſe<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> God is on our ſide, and therfore we feare not what the Pope or any other Carnalite can doe againſt vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, where and when is this horne erected? Euen there &amp; then, where and in what place the worlds force is to repreſſe the ſame, euen in the houſe of his ſeruant <hi>Dauid.</hi> When did Iſrael féele moſt the preſence of the horne? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Exod. 14.21 23.27.</note> 
               <hi>Pharao</hi> entred with greateſt rage, to deſtroy the Lordes heritage. When did <hi>Daniel</hi> perceiue his might, and where?<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 6.14.19.22.</note> Euen when his friend the Kyng wanted ſtrength to helpe him, and in the place
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:226:16"/> prouided for his deſtruction? Where did<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Reg. 19.14 18. Ro. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>Helias</hi> the good Prophet beholde this wonderfull horne erected? But where idolatrie had preuayled ouer all, and then alſo, when not one ſéemed to ſtand with the Lord. And did not Iſraell now decay? and the heathen enter into their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Was not <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe aboue al per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted? Then &amp; there did the Lord ſend his promiſed horne Chriſt our Lorde, by whoſe ſapience the wiſedome of all fleſh is proued fooliſhneſſe, and through whoſe ſtrength<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 12.29</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrong armed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſpoyled of his treaſure. Be of good comfort, O thou little flock afflicted, for the Lord hath, and wil haue his Chriſt to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Io. 16.33.</note> victorie.<note place="margin">Mar. 3.27. Luc. 11.21.</note> Yea, death is the inſtrument of life, and he maketh perſecution to bee the ſéede time of his Goſpel, and the bloud of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, the budding time of the ſame. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore alwayes with this &amp; other ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the holy Scripture, take comfort thou that truſteſt in the Lord: And let the experiment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt perſecution in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land aſſure thée that the power of this horne is eftſones encreaſed. Where and when did this Chriſt ſhewe forth to our
<pb facs="tcp:226:17"/> age his might? But when the bloud of his ſaintes, in our Engliſh bloudy Church, became as riuers of water, and in the time of their greateſt pride and ripenes of their Butchers actes? Then and there hath the Lord againe in this nation erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Chriſt and Goſpell, and from the priſon of the Tower, hath to the Throne and diademe of this land, rayſed his more then halfe dead <hi>Elizabeth</hi> our godly and gracious Quéene, vnder whom the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of the decayed walles of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, are greatly repayred once againe. God make vs mindfull of his mercies, &amp; thankfull for his benefites: And giue her Maieſtie ſuch encreaſe of his zealous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that the remnant of the <hi>Hydra</hi> and ſeuen headed beaſt may be baniſhed this nation, that in her gracious raigne, and by her godly hand with the ſtate of her ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and ciuil gouernment in God, as Gods holy inſtruments, Chriſt alone may be erected, as he is ſet downe by the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 132.17</note> 
               <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> to be our ſtrength &amp; our light. So ſhal her daies be many, her throne<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Sam. 12.14.15. Ioſ. 1.7.8. Deut. 28.7.</note> eſtabliſhed, and her and our enemies vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aſhamed. And in the meane ſpace,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:226:17"/> graunt vs O Lord (for Chriſtes ſake) true and perfect obedience to her Maieſtie, with pacient abyding, in humble peace, till the time which thou haſt ſet to frame her heroical heart further, to thoſe things which ſhall moſt ſound forth thy glory, her Maieſties honour, and the profite of thy Church: that ſo we may depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſt our horne of ſaluation, &amp; God of ſtrength.</p>
            <p>The Prophet not contented to ſtaye with this ſummary ſpéech, dilateth the ſame more amplie, &amp; ſayth as followeth in the next verſe.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>3</label> As he ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophets, which haue ben ſince the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</q>
            <p>Leaſt the ſaluation by him now prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in Chriſt, ſhould ſéeme to the world a new noueltie, fréeed from vtilitie and truth, he voucheth the ſame to be long ſith, determined of God: and the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to all ages before, by the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb facs="tcp:226:18"/> in their times.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice omnipotent to Satan at the fal of <hi>Adam,</hi> vntill the houre of this ioyful ſong, ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as to our certaine ſtay, the written word of God. As if he had ſayd, other ſauing health to looke for at the handes of God, then hée hath promiſed, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the ſame by him ſet and geuen, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to his promiſe, is mere wickednes. To geue credite to his word, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe therto, is true godlines. Wherfore come hither ye ſonnes of God, this is the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 3.15. &amp; 22.12.</note> promiſed ſéed, the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eſa. 7.14. &amp; 9.6</note> little ſtone, the virgins ſonne,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſa. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſſe</hi> his braunch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> and the anoynted Sauiour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord promiſed by al the prophets ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world. This verſe exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as by hand to our ſences excellent matter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that to the whole world, aſwell before Chriſt as ſince,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Dan. 2.34.45.</note> and till the laſt day and houre of the ſame world, there is no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be looked for (by that periſhing world) els where: then in <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, &amp; in and by the horne Chriſt Ieſus alone, by God, and not men, erected vp in all ſight, in that houſe, not ſet with, or vnder other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:226:18"/> helpes, but alone and aboue, all other ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their helpe at him. Of ſaintes the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is of moſt worthy fame, yet is ſhe farre of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 4.12</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing power to helpe in earth the ſonnes of men. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhe in her life for a leſſon till the end of death to all <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell being called vpon of the ſeruitors at the mariage, ſayth:<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer he bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you do (ſpeaking of her ſonne Christ) ſe that ye do it.</hi> And when <hi>Elizabeth</hi> this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prieſtes wife had ſaluted her, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Gods mercie to be the cauſe and ſayd:<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luc. 46</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord. &amp;c.</hi> And my ſpirite eke reioyceth in God (my Sonne) which is my Sauiour: for els had I wyth the reſt of the ſinfull world, both ſoule and bodie periſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall fire, had not this Chriſt by the ſpirite of God my Lord bene concei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and borne, not of me alone, but to and nor me alſo.</p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly he hath promiſed by al his Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phets (to deliuer vs from error) that this Chriſt is not to be found els where then in<note n="(a)" place="margin">Luc. 1.32.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which as all falſe Chriſtes are deſcried, ſo alſo the true
<pb facs="tcp:226:19"/> Church is hereby approuedly knowne. For as after the fleſh Chriſt is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 1.1 Luc. 3.23.</note> line of <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſo ſpiritually <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth his new Church, and in the ſame wiſe Chriſt is by the Prophets called ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drie times <hi>Dauid,</hi> aſwell by<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iere. 30.9 Eze. 34.23.</note> 
               <hi>Jeremie</hi> as <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is propheſied, to ſerue God and <hi>Dauid</hi> their king, vz. chriſt the ſonne of <hi>Dauid.</hi> For <hi>Dauid</hi> was now long ſith departed to the Lord, and again ſayth the Lord, I will ſet vp a ſhepherd ouer them, euen my ſeruaunt <hi>Dauid.</hi> &amp;c. And my ſeruaunt <hi>Dauid</hi> (that is Chriſt) ſhalbe the Prince among them, I the lord haue ſpoken it. Therefore (good Reader) of force it muſt be ſo. The houſe wherin this Princely <hi>Dauid</hi> raigneth, and this prieſtly Prophet teacheth, is the church of true Iſraelites, the vnfayned houſe of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Luc. 1.33.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob,</hi> to the which and for the which,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> the Angels diſcend, and aſcend dayly, by the commaundement of our King, to the miniſtring comfort of his elect. This Chriſtes church where this horne is erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is builded not by mans wiſedome, nor mayntained by popiſh policie and diueliſh diuinitie, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 16.18</note> builder
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:226:19"/> hereof is Chriſt himſelfe, and by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion his Prophets before him, which by his<note n="(d)" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.21.</note> ſpirite &amp; word builded the harts of the fathers to the fayth in his erected ſonne. And euer ſince his<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ephe. 4.11.</note> Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts Paſtours, Doctors and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, which<note n="(f)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23</note> receiue of his holy Goſpel, and therewith edifie the church, are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe<note n="(g)" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.10.11.</note> builders of this holy temple and houſe of our heauenly <hi>Dauid.</hi> Of which houſe<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ephe. 1.22. &amp; 5.23.</note> Chriſt is the head and chiefe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone. The<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eph. 2.19.20.21.22</note> familie and building of this houſe are ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtolical and Euangelicall Doctrine are brought to the rules which are therein ſet, by the Lord herein erected: of him alſo to the ſame end they haue their name, eate of his bread and worke (as hée is by calling in ſuch good workes, as are of the ſame Lord<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ephe. 2.10.</note> for them prepared euen from the time of calling, till the laſt houre of the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 20.8</note> penies receite. The continual<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10.11. Ephe. 4.11.12.13.</note> building of this <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, is by preaching the word of truth, not by popiſh preſſing in of falſe Doctrine: by geuing the ſacraments of the Lord to the people, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue of the Lord<note n="(d)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23</note> receiued them.
<pb facs="tcp:226:20"/> And not without commiſſion, and againſt the word to take the ſame from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and offer them vp to the Lord as doe the Papiſtes. Alſo to kéepe the houſe in order, by ciuil and eccleſiaſticall gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the lawe of Chriſt our <hi>Dauid.</hi> By this and ſuch like building, where ſo euer the Church is thus ſet vp, the ſame is true <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe.</p>
            <p>And where the power of this horne, is in the hartes of the people, by the worke of Gods ſpirite ſurely ſetled, and through the inſtrument and organ of preaching, the ſame Chriſt is naked, and without corruption in Doctrine,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> deſcribed ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, and depaynted ſo plaine wyth the penſell of the Scriptures that hee is to them manifeſted, as hée is of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther geuen, the onely promiſed Chriſt crucified, our<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> ſaluation, redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; iuſtification,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Deut. 18.15 Act. 7.37.</note> that Prophet, the onely<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 20. &amp; 7.17.21.28.</note> Prieſt, and our Kyng, and that all men by ſuch meanes are<note n="(e)" place="margin">Io. 14.6.</note> drawen alone to the Father by hym: there maye wée aſſure our ſelues, that that Church and Nation is <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, and therein is Chriſt to be found,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:226:20"/> erected for our ſaluation.<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> Againſt this building, the gates of Hell ſhall not preuayle. For as many as beleue in him, ſhall<note n="(g)" place="margin">Io. 3.14.15.</note> not periſh wyth the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent Sathans ſting, but by this holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, voyd of poyſon (Chriſt Ieſus,) ſhal haue eternall life. Agaynſt this church and to the ſubuerſition of his houſe, the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Apo. 2.1.15 17.</note> old enemie hath ſet him ſelfe wyth his whole power, continually to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame, and hath ſo preuayled in the eyes of men, that this houſe, hath eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones ſéemed, a forſaken cottage in the Lords vineyard, and the familie deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But euen when it ſéemed of leaſt value, then from the handes of ſuch ſtrength, the mightie God hath valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken of that number ſuch as ſhoulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue his houſe elſwhere. And wheras y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ſeketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this houſe: God by his might vſeth the ſame another way &amp; that to two principall ends. Firſt to teach other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 8.4</note> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they are diſperſed that heauenly doctrine, which els they had not known. And ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that at their returne they might bring w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them againe not only his word &amp; law,
<pb facs="tcp:226:21"/> but therwith many mo children, begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that time, by the perſecuted goſpel, eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones to the enlarging of the borders of that late nobled church.<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Sam. 22.16.</note> Go and kill (ſayth raging <hi>Saule</hi>) the prieſtes of the Lord, (which were the remnant of <hi>Elie,</hi>) for their hand is with <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; they haue not bewrayed him to me. At whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, that curſed <hi>Doeg</hi> did kill of them <hi>85.</hi> prieſtes of the Lord, that were the lynnin <hi>Ephod.</hi> Their Citie<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Sam. 22.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>Nob</hi> alſo hee deſtroyed from the moſt, to the leaſt, ſome, and all, for the hate he bare to them that fauoured <hi>Dauid.</hi> What then? Did he herewith kil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church? No ſurely. In this ſharpe perſecution <hi>Abimeleck</hi> his ſonne called <hi>Autathar,</hi> one of theſe prieſts eſcaping, fled to <hi>Dauid,</hi> which was him-<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Sam. 21.10.</note> ſelfe alſo from the furie of the ſayde <hi>Saule,</hi> fled to <hi>Achiſh</hi> the Kyng of <hi>Gath,</hi> a heathen prince, where both hée had ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and <hi>Auiathar</hi> continued with him to the continuall encreaſe<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Sam. 23.9</note> of Gods Church.</p>
            <p>Note here with me (good Reader) that God by his prouidence doth vſe the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hand of <hi>Saule,</hi> whoſe purpoſe was to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:226:21"/> deſtroy by his kingly power, both prieſt and people, in Gods Church to an other end, for he made him his inſtrument, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by to ſpreade the ſame his church among the gentiles, that not only in that place their harts might haue experiment of his power, but that alſo his Church of Ieſus then, to the comfort of the ſame nowe, might behold his ſecret work, far paſſing al their expectations, which was to foſter for a ſeaſon in ſuch flight, ſuch two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal perſons, as after ſhould erect that per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequuted cauſe and people, in the ſame perſequuted Nation, and that by no leſſe meane, then whereby for a time, the ſame was repreſſed, nor in any other place then in <hi>Saules</hi> ſeate (that is to ſay) Dauid hys faithfull foſtred king, and Auiathar, his good preſerued preſt. When cruel<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. Re. 11. 2. Cr. 22.10</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalia,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Ahaſia</hi> King of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, ſought to extirpe the kings ſéede, that ſhe might vſurpe the kingdome, ſhée murthering the reſt, did ſhe deſtroy the houſe? No, <hi>Joaſh</hi> one of his ſonnes was from her hand of ſlaughter ſaued, &amp; that by the hand of a maid his Siſter, till the time that the Lord had appointed, for the
<pb facs="tcp:226:22"/> ſaid Ioaſhe the true King to enter into his realme, and ſo to render recompence, by iuſt pay of deſerued death, to that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vſurper <hi>Athalia,</hi> which after Seuen yeares he brought to paſſe, ſetting this re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued Ioaſh in his fathers ſeate.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 2.16. Illiricus ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 1. lib. 1. cap. 30. fol. 22.</note> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod alſo ſéeking by the death of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes to kill the Meſſias, not only failed of his pray, but was himſelfe deuoured of GODS Iuſtice. And although the Papiſtes followe theſe and ſuch other their forefathers in like murthering cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, as lately in Englande, and ſince in Fraunce: yet will the LORDE, and hath the LORDE ſet vppe, (as he hath promiſed by the mouthe of all his Prophetes ſince the worlde began) his Chriſte, to bee his ſtrength in ſpite of them. Who yéelding as it were for the tyme, doth thereby nothing looſe, but leſſe ableth, the aduerſarye: While by Sathans furie the Churche is elſe where gone, as before is ſaide, to bringe foorth (by her Chriſte) in a more quiet place, many moe Children. At whoſe returne, the loſſe of her former are reſtored, with infinite moe her borders enlarged, her
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:226:22"/> honoure encreaſed, and her fame ſpred ouer all. For the LORD her ſtrength, hath, and will<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mic. 7.10.</note> (confounding her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and treading them in the mire) geue her the victorie. Adde vnto the holy Scriptures teſtes, our own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented teſtymony, in the late perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting time, of Queene Marie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with well conſider the encreaſe of hys Church, &amp; number of her children, which by the perſecuted Preachers then, with others their brethren ſince, through their miniſterie in the Goſpell, are begot in Chriſt, and in thys Churche of Englande foſtered, to the praiſe, and in the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame our Lord. To conclude let euery faithfull man aſſure himſelfe of the ſame continuall worke of God in his church, to the end of the world. For his<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 33.18. Pſal. 34.15.</note> eyes with remembrance of his promiſe, are euer ouer the righteous, to performe, to all perpetuity, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which by ſo many holy witneſſes, as his patriarks &amp; prophets, he hath to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame promiſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time ſo aſſuredly. Now let vs repaire again to our prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> who proceding, doth ſet forth at large y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> performed promiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:226:23"/> God, and the effectes of the ſame, to his beloued Church, ſaying as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> That he would ſend vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce, from our enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and from the hands of all that hate vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>5</label> That he would ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towardes our Fathers, and remember his holy coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>6</label> And the othe which he ſware to our Father Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>7</label> Which was, that he would graunt to vs, that we being deliuered out of the handes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:226:23"/> of our enemies, ſhould ſerue him with out feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> All the daies of our life, in holines and righteouſnes before him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This whole text dependeth vppon the former expounded verſe. <hi>As he promiſed to our fore. &amp;c.</hi> And declareth by manifeſt proofe, the faithfulnes of God, which hath fulfilled his promiſes and oth, not by the Prophets alone, but long before made to the Patriarkes, that was to <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaying:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 12.3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> I will bleſſe them that bleſſe thée, and I wil curſe them that curſe thée. And alſo thy<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 22.17</note> ſéede ſhall poſſeſſe the gates of their enemies, and in thy ſéede ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and this promis, he confirmed with an<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 22.16</note> oth which Zacherie here repeateth, ſaying, I haue ſworne by my ſelfe, I will bleſſe thée, and multiplie thy ſeede. His li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing couenant alſo with <hi>Abraham</hi> was this, Moreouer<note n="(d)" place="margin">Gen. 17.7</note> I will ſtabliſh my loue,
<pb facs="tcp:226:24"/> betwéene me and thée, and thy ſéede after thée, in their generations for an euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting couenant, to be god vnto thée, and to thy ſéede after thée. And I will geue thée, and thy ſéede after thée, the land wherein thou art a ſtraunger: euen all the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> for an euerlaſting poſſeſſion, &amp; I wilbe their God. And with our Father Dauid he made a couenant alſo, which by oth eke he eſtabliſhed, that it might be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Heb. 6.17.</note> moſt firme: and now in ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding his Chriſt (ſaith <hi>Zachary</hi> he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the ſame, which erſt thus ſpake, I<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 89.3.</note> haue made a couenant with my choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> I haue ſworne to Dauid my ſeruant, thy ſéed wil I ſtabliſh for euer, and ſet vp thy throne from generation to generations. Againe I haue found Dauid my ſeruant, with my holy oyle haue I anointed him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> Therefore mine hand ſhalbe eſtabliſhed with him and my arme ſhall ſtrengthen him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> The enemy ſhall not oppreſſe him, neither ſhal the wicked hurt him. But I will deſtroy his foes before his face, and plague them that hate him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> My truth and my mercy ſhalbe with him, and in my name ſhall his horne be exalted. And al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:226:24"/> that theſe and ſuch other couenants by GOD, with the Fathers made, for, and to them, and the reſt of his Churche, may ſéeme to ſound temporall thinges: yet beſide that this Pſalme ſheweth them to be ſpirituall, our Prophet here, as a moſte true Paraphraſt, expoundeth the ſame couenantes and promiſes, by othe of the LORDE alſo confirmed (to their infallible ſtabilitie) to be vnderſtanded of vs ſpiritually, and in Chriſt to poſſeſſe them, by him likewyſe, as victorius men, and more then conqueroures to triumph ouer and againſt our<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> ſpirituall enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſinne, Sathan, the worlde, and the fleſh,<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note> Principalities, powers, world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouernoures, (that is to ſay, ſuch as gouerne by, and for the worldes luſte,) Princes of darknes of this world, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall wickedneſſes, which are in high pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and whatſoeuer openeth it ſelfe to the worke of our Saluation. Neither did Chriſt deliuer the Iewes from the tir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and bondage of the Romaines, but yéelding himſelfe to that authoritye,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 22.17.</note> paid the tribute thither due: Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge vs thereby to looke for a further, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:226:25"/> a more bleſſed deliuerance, of which as be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh to the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> And the Angelles from Heauen preached the ſame to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſaying, he ſhalbe called<note n="(c)" place="margin">Math. 1.21</note> Ieſus. For he ſhall ſaue his people, (not from temporall gouernment of Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) but from (the ſpiritual captiuity of) their ſinnes. That being ſo, from feare of ſin, ſathan, hell, world, and fleſh, ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſafely deliuered, they may ſerue the Lord, not with Iewiſh rites, or popiſh deuotion, but with<note n="(d)" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.22</note> ſinceritie of hart, &amp;<note n="(e)" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.8.</note> purenes of handes in euery place, in true holyneſſe, and like righteouſneſſe by him accepted, and in his ſight frée from hipocriſy, al the daies of their life. Lo this is the fruite of the bleſſed promiſes, othe and couenantes, which our Prophet here ſpeaketh of. This is the victory which God geueth to his faithfull fighting ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and ſanctified people. On this ſorte ſhall they poſſeſſe the gates of their enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they ſhal through Chriſt their head, remaine and dwell as Lordes ouer all thinges. And ſhall treade Satan vnder their<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 9.30.31</note> féete, notwithſtanding his dayly aſſaltes and ſubtil fight. The battel is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:226:25"/> Sathan and the ſoule of man, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth wyth mans lyfe, and is fought in the fielde of a good conſcience, enduring by fayth till death, for both partes ſound the retyre. But the (a) victory, by Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite is euer aſſured to the faythfull, and ſhall be perfected wyth (b) Chriſt in his kingdome, to our endles happie and moſt bleſſed ſtate. Now hauing the text thus opened, by Gods mercies, and grace of his ſpirit, let vs according to our former rule obſerue ſome ſuch profitable notes, as the ſame doth reache apparantly, to our conſiderations. And firſt in this ſeconde verſe of this ſection, (for of the firſt, we ſhall ſpeake more herafter, Chriſt ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,) let vs vpon the wordes note, that the Fathers, Patriarkes and Prophets, albeit they are of the prophet here called, and that truly (holy) yet did not their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe demerit ſuch great treaſures, and heauenly fruitfulneſſe, eyther for their ſelues or their poſterity, as by his words he here expreſſeth. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But ſayth the prophet (well inſtructed in the doctrine of truth) the Lorde was there vnto brought to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes our Fathers, by his mere mercy,
<pb facs="tcp:226:26"/> that wyth them he ſhould make ſo So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne and Honorable a couenaunt.</p>
            <p>And if the Fathers whoſe holineſſe the ſacred Scriptures ſo much recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, had not wherwyth to meritte the couenaunt of peace wyth God, Where ſhall theyr Chyldren obteyne ſuche pryce. Naye, ſuch as haue ſought by theyr worthyneſſe and Obedience to the Lawe, ſet downe by the LORDE in his woorde, to haue Iuſtification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, becauſe of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered vertues, ſuche I ſaye haue loſte that they ſought for, nor could atteyne to that they would, to ſaye deliuerance from their Spirituall Enemies, and to be accompted iuſt before the Lorde, the Apoſtle ſo witneſſeth ſaying.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom 9.30.31.</note> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell which followed the Lawe of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, coulde not atteyne to the Lawe of Righteouſneſſe, becauſe they ſought it not by Fayth, but as it were by the workes of the Lawe, for they haue ſtombled at the ſtombling ſtoane, that is, they are offended at the Chriſte which GOD hath ſet to be the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe for his people, and refuſinge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:226:26"/> him and his merites, they reſt vppon the ſhyuering ſtaffe of their imagined ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe. But the Gentilles (ſayth <hi>Paule</hi>) which folowed not righteouſnes haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined vnto righteouſnes, euen the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes that is of faith, that is to ſay, the true righteouſnes which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be bought by deſert, but is atteined by faith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe of God. Here let our enemies the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts wey well with them ſelues how far they are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſenſe of truth. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers accepted with God in great fauor receiued not otherwiſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his mercies his promiſed chriſt, &amp; in him their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; ful deliuerance, &amp; alſo if they ſéeking him vnfeynedly with ſinceritie of harte, came ſo far ſhort of merit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> had not the exhibiting mercy, preuented his prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked iuſtice the ſame our fathers had peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe. How then can they, or man or angell for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, obteine for vs ſaluation, or remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſinnes, by any merit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>céede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a creature or creaturs? The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtes,<note place="margin">Popiſh me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.</note> are eyther the weight of their Maſſing Sacrifyces, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the bloud of Martyres, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the abſolute power of theyr Pope, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> or that (which they thinke) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fayleth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the good workes of men.
<pb facs="tcp:226:27"/> men. As for the meritte of their maſſe, out of all queſtion, it meriteth neyther pardon with God the father, nor place in the church of chriſt his ſonne. But it being vſed doth derogate (as much as it may) the Power of Chriſt whiche alone of God is ſet vp, to &amp; for his church in <hi>Dauids</hi> houſe: and arrogateth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Chriſt and his office to that abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idoll. But (beloued children of God) geue attentiue eare to the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call wordes written to the <hi>Hebrues,</hi> and thou ſhalt plainely perceiue by the power of Gods ſpirite, that the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10.14.</note> one oblation of chriſtes naturall body on the croſſe, in his death hath for euer, not onely taken away from vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of God, &amp; reward of ſin, but hath therewith abrogated, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne ſacrifices, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by himſelfe in his written word, and alſo hath taken away (for all times to come) all power from any man or angell to ſet vp, any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacrifice or oblation propitiatory in place thereof: wherefore he ſayth by the will of God (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10.9.</note> Chriſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of God) we are ſanctified, euen by the Offering of the bodye of Ieſus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:226:27"/> Chriſt once made. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> And in the ſame place hée denyeth that the Sacrifyces commaunded of GOD can longer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, becauſe that the true Sacrifyce Chriſt Ieſus is alreadye Offered, of which and whom they were Fygures. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>12</label> And alſo denyeth that this Chriſt is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more to be Offered, but playnely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmeth hym after that his once Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to fitte for euer at the Ryght hande of the Father, and ſhall not thence come, till his enemies<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 110. 1. Cor. 13.25</note> be made his footſtole. And that all men might be Satiſfyed, he addeth a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherefore, ſaying<note n="(c)" place="margin">Heb. 10.14.</note> for wyth one Offering hath he conſecrated for euer thoſe that are Sanctifyed. And moreouer he calleth the Holy Ghoſt for witneſſe of the ſame as in the <hi>15.</hi> and <hi>16.</hi> verſes following, and ſo concludeth vp his Aſſertion. That ſince Chriſt Ieſus hath thus redéemed vs,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10.17.</note> there is no more Offering for ſinne of one or other, but in place thereof there is (ſayth hée) ſet vppe to and for vs, an entering into lyfe by a more beautifull manner, which hée there calleth a newe and liuing way,
<pb facs="tcp:226:28"/> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs through the perſon Chriſt, which is our hye Prieſt: who requireth not ſacrifice of vs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>23</label> but an approching hart made pure in conſcience and body from ſinne by fayth &amp;c. Therefore away wyth your Popiſhe traſh, your maſking maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes can no longer ſhaddowe the trueth. Further I pray you, whether doth God at any time accept the man for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyce, or the Sacrifyce for the man? I trow the Text ſayth, that God regarded not<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>Cayn,</hi> or his Sacrifyce, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily he accepted <hi>Habell</hi> and his Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which ſturred vp <hi>Cayn</hi> his wrath to kill his Brother <hi>Habell.</hi> Here it is plaine, God reſpecteth firſt the man, and then his ſacrifice, if the man be not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, his ſacrifyce is abhominable, as in the Prophet<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſa. 1.10.11.12.13.14.15</note> 
               <hi>Eſay,</hi> the Lord reproueth the Iewes for their paynefull ſeruing in will worſhippe. and ſayth, he abhorreth their deuiſes, and will not turne towards them with fauor, though their ſacrifices be coſtly, becauſe they are ſinful that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them. And the people for whom they are offred, are the children of ſinne, their handes are full of bloud, yea, &amp; they geue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:226:28"/> to God that which he aſketh not, and therefore diſlyking vtterly thereof, he ſayth,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eſa. 1.16.</note> who required this at your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des? And there teacheth them to amend from their Wicked wayes, to waſhe them from their ſinnes, &amp; ſo will he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them and their Oblations. Chriſt himſelfe alſo doth nothing more pacifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fathers wrath, in his moſt holy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, then in reſpecte, that according to the Fathers wyll, he hath yéelded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for an Oblation as he was of him appoynted, by his written woorde ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10.5.</note> body haſt thou ordeyned me, and loe I am here to doe thy wyll. Let the Pope and his Clergye (as Chriſt here doth) ſhew vs the heauenly God or Father his holy written will, for their accepted perſones in Sacrifyſing for the Quicke and Deade, and for ſuche their fayned propitiatorie Sacrifyces: and we will not ſhame for loſſe of credit to ſubcribe vnto them. But this they can not, and therefore they hate the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and would not that wée ſhoulde Studye in them: Becauſe they knowe that there by their Idolatrye is bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:226:29"/> and their Trecherie made knowen, and that both they and their Sacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are wyth <hi>Cayn</hi> odious in Gods ſight. Oh that therefore we coulde wyth our <hi>Zachary</hi> retourne the Phraſe of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe ſpeache to the Forge, that fyrſt framed the ſame, and coulde acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our Saluatſon to conſiſt in Gods mercye alone, by the meritte of his Sonne Chriſt in that his Sacrifyce, in his<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24</note> naturall Bodye Crucifyed on the croſſe once for al, &amp; al ages. By the which (ſayth the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>) wée are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from Sinne to liue in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſay. 53.5.2</note> for by the <hi>(b)</hi> ſtrypes of Ieſus Chriſtes Death wée are made whole. The bloud of Sayntes, is their other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined meritte for mennes Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Gods fauour. But (good reader) of Sayntes the Apoſtles are chiefe, and hath not Chriſt taught them to ſaye, forgeue O Lorde our ſinnes?<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 6.12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Hath not the chiefe of them whoſe lyfe was angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, whoſe perſon to death was eftſoons aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſailed (<hi>Paule</hi> I mean) hath not he writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; doth not he therby yet ſpeake, that the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Gal. 3.8.9.10.11.12.13.14. &amp;c.</note> merit of eternall life is Gods mercie, not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:226:29"/> mans merit? And yet ſpeaking of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringes and bloud of martired ſaintes, for the teſtimonie of God and his Goſpel, he acknowledgeth that the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 8.18.</note> afflictions of them in this life, are not worthy of the glory which ſhall be ſhewed to them in the triumphant kingdome of our heauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father. But their merit (ſayth hée) is Gods loue, who hath choſen them to bée his ſonnes, and hath (ſayth hée) annexed them with Chriſt, as heires of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Note well eternall life commeth not by the bloud and afflictions of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, not by purchaſe of mens merits, but by the inheritaunce geuen vs in Chriſt thorough Gods mercie. Thus good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thou ſéeſt that this popiſh poſt is rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for age and want of heart, what ſhal we ſaye of the third matter, the Popes pardon? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Surely if neither his God the Maſſe, nor his ſaintes bloud can helpe, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther can his pardons any thing profite thée, for they are all of one force, &amp; haue all a like authoritie. I néede not longer to ſtand in the confutation of ſuch a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked taile of the people, that boaſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bée the onely head of Gods church
<pb facs="tcp:226:30"/> in earth, controler in the heauens, prince in Purgatorie, and Maſter of Hell. Bée not offended that I call him that tayle of the people, for the warrant is geuen me, by the holy Ghoſt, ſo to terme him.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 9.15.</note> 
               <hi>The auncient and honorable man, he is the head, ſaith Eſay, and the Prophet that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth lies, he is the tayle of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The laſt of Popiſh merites, are good workes which can not merit Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for either they precede, or folow faith. If they go<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 14.23.</note> before fayth, they are ſinne, and therefore moue Gods furie, rather then merite his mercie. If they followe faith, they then merite not that which of God is giuen before their birth, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe by ſuch fruite, what well<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted trée brought them forth. But as no trée meriteth life by the Apple which hée beareth, but faſt ſetled in the ground, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth of the iuyce that commeth from the roote, ſo the faythful merite not Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour (which is their life) by their works, (the fruites of their fayth) but ſetled and grafted into Chriſt their foundation, they doe receiue their common life from the ſame roote, by the ſappe his ſpirite which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:226:30"/> from him is ſent and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 14, 26.</note> geuen, to euery of them ſufficiently, to life eternall. What, ſhall we then not worke?<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> God forbid: Alwayes do and continue in that which is good, but cauſe not a good thing commaunded of GOD, to become a peſtilent euill to thy conſcience. Liue and walke in good workes, which God hath prepared for thée:<note place="margin">The end of good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</note> but let them bée done to the ſame end which GOD hath directed to them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Namely, that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward déede in them, may expreſſe thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fayth in Chriſt our Lord.<note place="margin">Phil. 5. Heb. 6.10 2. Pet. 1.5</note> And further that the Church of GOD may bée profited by them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But chiefely that by the ſame, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> many mouthes ſéeing thy faythfull actes may bée prepared and ſtirred vp to<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> glorifie thy Father which is in heauen. This is the voice of holy ſcripture, declaring the end of good works to be as we haue ſaid, but that they merit not, <hi>Paule</hi> playnely ſheweth to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> for and to al in the perſon of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> ſaying: if<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 4.2. &amp;c</note> 
               <hi>Abraham were iuſtified by workes, he hath wherein to reioyce, but not with God. For what ſaith the Scripture? Abraham beleeued God, and it was counted
<pb facs="tcp:226:31"/> to him for righteouſnes. Now to him that worketh, the wages is not counted by fauour but by debt, hut to him that worketh not (vz. to merit thereby) but beleueth in him that iuſtifieth the wicked, his faith is counted for righteouſnes.</hi> Thus then we ſée, that the fathers with vs haue not merited Chriſt our onely felicitie, but Gods mercie and loue ſurmounting (as I may reuerently ſay) his iuſtice in iuſt wrath, hath not of dutie, but by loue, geuen, and not ſold to vs that beleue in him his Sonne Chriſt, that we<note n="(c)" place="margin">Io. 3.16.</note> ſhould not periſh, but by him being deliuered from our enemies, ſhould haue euerlaſting life and power in him to ſerue him, in this time of our mortall fleſh in all holines, &amp; vertuous exerciſes before him, al the dayes of our life. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer I note that our Lord God will not haue vs to dwell in vncertainties for our ſaluation, and therefore he ſendeth vs to his written word, where his promiſes &amp; couenant is by his owne ſpirit ſet downe to all fleſh, for the which cauſe Zacharie hath relation in this verſe to the<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.10</note> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten promiſes and couenaunt. And to the ſame ſayth<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 20.31</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> alſo is the Goſpell
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:226:31"/> written to vs now, that wee ſhould by that written truth, beléeue that Ieſus is the Chriſt the ſonne of God, and that in beleuing we might haue life through his name. As for the vnwritten verities of the Papiſtes, as they are counterfet and forged of their owne brayne: ſo can they bring no comfort to the conſcience of the wounded man, or ſatiſfaction to the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſoule that<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 5.6. &amp; 11.38.</note> laboureth to ſéeke the water of life, which God doth geue to thoſe that hunger &amp; thirſt after the ſame. For nothing els worke they,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10.14</note> but draw to hell all ſuch as truſt and are led by them. But he that thirſteth after the water of life: els where then in the written ſacred ſcriptures can it not be found. Séeke this water in the Scripture therfore (good Reader) and the Lord will make heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="(c)" place="margin">Io. 4.14. &amp; 7.37.38.</note> riuers to flowe out of thée, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou ſhalt ſatiſfie thine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the ſame Chriſt fully, and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo to bring many other to the ſame<note n="(d)" place="margin">Io. 17.2</note> ſaluation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which the knowledge of the Lord, by his ſpirite in the ſcriptures hath wrought in thée. Laſt of all in this verſe let vs marke diligently, that not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:226:32"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in chriſt Ieſus, God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs partakers of his holy couenant. Or yet by any other meanes are we kept within the compaſſe therof, then by the cauſe it ſelfe which is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 4.12</note> Chriſt the Lord, the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Apo. 1.8. &amp; 21.6. &amp; 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of the ſame: So voucheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſaying, in<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ro. 4. Gal. 3.16.</note> thy ſéede which is Chriſt, ſhal al nations be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>The obſeruations of the ſixt verſe, are alſo comfortable and profitable. Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table when we perceiue that our ſinnes deſerue the breach of Gods loue and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme iudgement: yet God in his mercie doth promiſe &amp; ſweare to kéepe his word giuen to the fathers, and to deliuer vs from the ſayd iudgment, as the Prophet in the text ſayth,<note place="margin">Verſe. 6. And the oth which hee ſware. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and the oth which hee ſwere. &amp;c.</hi> The profite hereof enſueth, in the doctrine following. In no caſe may we gather, becauſe God is ſayd here to ſweare, that his word without an oth is doubtefull, for the Scriptures euery where approue them abſolutely, Amen.</p>
            <p>Alſo Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth that<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 5 18. &amp; 24.35. Mar. 13.31.</note> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth ſhal paſſe, but not one iote of my word ſhall paſſe till all be fulfilled. And the Apoſtle ſayth, that the doctrine of the Lord is not<note n="(e)" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.17.18.19.20.</note> yea, and nay, but yea
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:226:32"/> and Amen. He<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> ſpeaketh the woord, ſayth <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; they were made,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.1. Ro. 1.19.20.</note> the times before vs till this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; witnes of time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beautifull heauens ſhew forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of God in his word, that the ſame is moſt true and ſtrong to the ſaluation, of al that beleue in Chriſt through it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we imagine that he did ſweare thereby to hiue vs example or warrant, to vſe vaine and blaſphemous othes (but leauing to the weaknes of our fayth<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 6.17</note> the Lord ſware the more to confirme his promiſes in vs) for he hath forbid vs to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his holy word, where<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 5.34.35.</note> nothing is permitted vs to ſweare by in heauen or earth, no not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heares of our head: but there are we commaunded to frame our harts to honeſtie &amp; truth, which ſhall out of all occaſion of othes &amp; blaſphemies from vs, &amp; ſo kepe farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces the accuſing<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mar. 9.44 Eſa. 66.24.</note> worme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, &amp; the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Zach. 5.4.</note> vengeance of god, which neuer departeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe of the ſwearer. Albeit ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we may &amp; ought to ſweare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of god,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ier. 4.2.</note> &amp; the end of controuerſies in &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt his people, being called therto or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt we ſweare in truth and righteouſnes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:226:33"/>
            <p>Here would I gladly helpe my countrey of England, (if in this place I might bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ſo large a licence) which much vſeth this kind of ſwearing in weſtminſter hal, and other the Tribunall ſeates of this land. Many of them ſweare, and ſweat to ſweare and offer othes, and both borowe and lend the ſame to ſatiſfie their friends, and what is the charge of an oth, for the moſt part many forceth not: ſo, to winne their expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by oth, they may diſpatch their propoſed intent. But learne a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle here of othes (good Rearder) and firſt what an oth is. <hi>An oth, is a taking Gods name to witneſſe, to the better and more ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 6.16. Deut. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>confirmasion of thoſe things which we vouch in communication or teſtes,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 28.20. Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>or els in co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenant or promiſe,</hi> aſſuring thoſe to whom we ſweare, that nothing but truth proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from vs.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. 1.24</note> Herein in his due place, god is greatly honoured and worſhipped, hereby we confeſſe him to be euery where preſent, to behold the hartes and actions of all men, to be a<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 1.18. Theſ. 4.6.</note> reuenger of euil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the offenders in this poynt. But if either falſely, or for any other reſpect then for his glories ſake, and the peace of his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:226:33"/> people, we ſweare, or ſéeke to ſweare, though it be true that we do ſweare, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we ſinne, though not in the ſubſtance of the matter, yet in the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall part therof: becauſe either the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the one, or dread of the other, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, bloud or other worldly reſpectes, compelleth vs therto, and not the ſorce of truth it ſelfe, and this God will plague. Surely he wil alſo plague al ſuch as mixt in their othes the creatures of heauen &amp; earth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God, by whom<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone we muſt ſweare being called therto.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 65.16</note> 
               <hi>He that ſweareth (ſayth Eſay) ſhal ſweare by the true and liuing God.</hi> And again <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith in the perſon of God,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſa. 45.23.</note> 
               <hi>Al knees ſhal bowe to me, and euery tongue ſhall ſweare by my name.</hi> And as this is commaunded in Scripture, ſo are we there forbidden to ſweare by them that are no Gods,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Exo. 23.13. Pſal. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>All that which J haue commaunded you, ſee that ye obſerue the ſame, and thinke not vppon the names of their Gods, nor let them be once na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of you.</hi> And in<note n="(d)" place="margin">Sopho. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sophony</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, and threatneth to deſtroy and cut of all thoſe that ſweare by God and by <hi>Malcham.</hi> That God <hi>Maazim</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:226:34"/> Maſſe, or ſuch blind<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ioſua 23.7</note> iudges as offer and geue charge to ſweare by God and all ſaintes, or either that wicked vſe, God &amp; our Lady, God and ſaint <hi>John. &amp;c.</hi> Or ſuch as not daring to ſweare, yet inuent to ſweare by fayned &amp; new found othes, as mat for Maſſe, and gob for GOD, and hods body and bloud for our Lordes bleſſed body and bloud. &amp;c. There is no leſſe wickedneſſe in the one then in the other, for therein we ſtill breake his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement that ſayth,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 5.34.</note> 
               <hi>ſweare not at all,</hi> and we declare thereby our willing deſire to blaſphemie, which as we dare not enter into, for feare of his vengeance: ſo wée frame our ſelues as néere thereto as wée can, by diueliſh daliance: much like to Maiſter <hi>Hardinges</hi> pleaſant ſpéech of our Ladies ſpiritual ſport with Chriſt her Sonne, when ſhée in the popiſh Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is prayed to ſaye <hi>lube natum. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſidering that theſe euils are to bée remoued, and that ſwearing is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſome reſpect of GOD permitted, but alſo wée haue now heard commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and is a chiefe part of the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and worſhippe of our God, let vs learne to ſerue him herein in true holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:226:34"/> and righteouſneſſe, ſuch as may wel bée accepted before him. The which to do wée, muſt obſerue that rule in ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which the Prophet geueth to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appointed to ſweare, ſaying:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iere. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt ſweare (ſayth he) in truth, in iudgement, and in righteouſnes.</hi> Foure poyntes he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to obſerue in our ſwearing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that wée ſweare by no leſſe then by the liuing God, by no dead coniured cake or other Idoll.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that we ſweare in <hi>veritate,</hi> in truth, as if he had ſayd, play not the hypocrite, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſweare not with lippes alone, but with the hart alſo, ſéeke not by any meanes to be deceiued in thy ſoule, or to deceaue others by thy craftines in ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Dare not to pronounce one part of thy mind to the hearing of the Iudge, and another ſecretly to thy ſelfe. As of late a Miniſter ryding to his reuerend Biſhop for a benefice, at his returne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly ſayd (as I am credibly informed,) that he vſed tofore him the ſame cunning figure of defection called <hi>calliditas,</hi> which in plaine Engliſh is lying craftines, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring outwardly to ſubſcribe &amp;c. and ſoftly ſaying to himſelf, as far forth as they are
<pb facs="tcp:226:35"/> warranted &amp;c. Now ſurely, to haue ſafe warrant of God, is neceſſarie for our ſubſcription in doctrine, but to ſweare to obſerue and to<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 22.23</note> allow of that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hée ſtandeth in doubt, is a halting with God, a mocking of men, and a manifeſt ſhew of an ill conſcience in him that vſeth the ſame, which can not bee farre from the curſe of God.<note place="margin">Ro. 14.23</note> Sweare truly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let heart and tongue goe together, and vouch both one thing, els thou doeſt heape Gods wrath vppon thine owne head.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third poynt of ſwearing is to ſweare in <hi>iudicio,</hi> that is, with diſcretion, not raſhly or ouerlightly, but firſt weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe why he ſweareth, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which by oth he is to witneſſe, the good that may come therof, and the wrath of God following falſe ſwearing: he is to ſweare truely, that which hee himſelfe knoweth by ſight, or ſelf hearing, and not to leane vpon other mens reportes. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, let no man frame himſelfe to ſweare for trifling things or lightly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked, but in mere neceſſitie, &amp; then with graue conſideration and reuerent regard
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:226:35"/> of Gods preſence, before whom wée all ſtand, whoſe eyes behold the déedes of all men, whoſe eares receaue the whiſpering ſpéech of the déepe diſſembling harte. Tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therefore to ſweare for light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or at euery mans firſt perſwaſion, for an oth is the extreme poynt of Gods ordinance to bée vſed of men, and before Magiſtrates to baniſh braules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and to conſerue the peace and vtilitie of his church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth and laſt poynt is, that wée ſweare in <hi>Justicia.</hi> Let not your othes, ſayth he, be contrary to right and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but thereby ſéeke to geue to euery man that which of right is due vnto him, whether in caſes pertayning to God, to godly Magiſtrates, or to any other ſorts of men. And let the loue of God, and of eour Chriſtian brethren, wyth regard of the onely truth, hée alwayes your guide in ſwearing, and not the faces of ſinfull men. In any caſe beware of too much credite in other men, geue thy ſelfe his true <hi>Iusticia,</hi> that is to ſay, let thine owne eyes, thy reaſon, thy conſcience, thy faith, thy honeſtie, thy perſon, with his name,
<pb facs="tcp:226:36"/> fame, and crauing credite, kéepe him ſelfe ſubiect to the Lord his God in holines, and righteouſnes, in the middle of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill world, al the dayes of thy lyfe. Farre bée it from thée to become the ſlaue of the riche in thy ſwearing, the foreſworne te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of thy leude prouoking landlord, or a chayned lumpe of fleſh to the bones of thy kindred, by ſuch meanes, or any wayes elſe to bée caried from the truth, to the hurt of an other, though hée bée thine enemie, or to the condemnation of thine owne ſoule, by a falſe othe to purchaſe thy friend his pleaſure. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if thou ſhalt embrace that which here thou art exhorted vnto, and ſhalt abhorre that which thou readeſt here forbidden of God, thou ſhalt in ſuch ſwearing bleſſe his name, and he ſhall acknowledge thée for his child, and in his Chriſt ſhall defend thée from the force and rage of the mighty wicked in earth, and ſhall geue thée in the end of this thy life thy reſting place and dwelling houſe, his holy Tabernacle the heauenly bliſſe, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> doth witneſſe in the fiftenth <hi>Pſalme</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note> moſt comfortably to the reading of the which I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:226:36"/> referre thée.</p>
            <p>Now are we come to that which we erſt promiſed vz. to ſpeake of our deliuerance from our enemies by this erected horne Chriſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. 7 That wee ſhould bee deliuered from the handes of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. &amp;c.</note> whereto god hath ſworne that we ſhould not only giue him the more credit, but alſo ſhuld frame our ſelues in him, to lead the life that ſuch redemption requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth at our hands. But this redemption reacheth to the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 10.14 Heb. 13.8</note> ends of the world, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what kind of enemies ſo euer, or in what ſort they bend their battrie againſt vs, God by this Scripture, with other his promiſes, hath aſſured vs the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſa. 54.15.</note> victory, and from our foes full deliuerance. Our enemies are ſinne, Satan, the world and the fleſh, who in all ages, haue not onely troubled the church &amp; people of god with groſſe and carnall vices, but haue ſet vp in the ſayde Church a fourme of<note n="(c)" place="margin">Exod. 32.1.</note> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion deuiſed in Hell, carying the title of holineſſe and Gods ſeruice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue more eaſely drawne the multitude of men, from GOD to ſuch ſinne, vnder the cloke of deuotion, to their perpetuall confuſion and ſhame. This imagined holineſſe and humane religion,
<pb facs="tcp:226:37"/> did Sathan firſt broche in the church of Ieſus vnder<note n="(a)" place="margin">Exo. 32</note> 
               <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and eftſones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the ſame as hée could, chaunging him ſelfe after the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iudg. 11.39. &amp; 17.18. 1. Sa. 28.8 1. Re. 11.4. &amp; 12.28. &amp; 16.31. &amp; 18.26. &amp; 21.9.10. 2. Re. 1.2 2. Para. 24.17.18. &amp; 25.14. &amp; 33.2.3 5.6.7. Dan. 3.1.2.3. &amp; 6.7.8.9 1. Macab. 2. Macab. wholy.</note> faſhion of euery age, preuayleth till the time of Chriſt, and the Phariſies, and ſince alſo, hath playd his part in the Synagoge of <hi>Rome,</hi> of whoſe filthie cup the Kynges and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth haue taſted, to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme<note n="(c)" place="margin">Apoc. 14.8 &amp; 18.3.</note> dronkennes.</p>
            <p>This is the greateſt enmitie that Sathan can worke to Gods people, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der coulour of ſéeking and ſeruing him, to drawe them quite from his Maieſtie, and in ſuch ſort blyndeth their eyes, and wyth his fierie Dartes ſo kendleth their carnall zeale, that in the will worſhippe of their owne inuention, they ſpare no coſt, or<note n="(d)" place="margin">Col. 2.23</note> ſhunne any payne, to ſéeme more then religious therein. In this our age the Church of England is vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wyth two horrible Impes, and meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of our enemie Sathan, as ſent of hym to moleſt our happie ſtate, to ſtoppe the ioyes that wée are to conceiue in our moſt comfortable Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:226:37"/>
            <p>The firſt imphe is the forraine papiſticall foe, the ſeconde is our domeſticall Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe hipocrites. The forrayne Papiſtes beyonde the ſeas, haue bent their force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the truth profeſſed here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and to encounter wyth the ſame, haue prepared a double ſhot agaynſt this frontire, our religion. The one ſhooting ſlaunder by rayling penne at the truth, and perſons profeſſing the ſame: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charged wyth treaſon and Popiſhe pouder, ſhooteth at the ſtate and perſon of our ſouereigne as at the Liefetenaunt of the Lordes bande. But from them both the Lorde in his great mercie, hath, and doth deliuer vs. And with the truth of his Goſpel, by ſuch habilitie, as he geueth to his church and miniſterie, in theſe our dayes doth ſo ouertake the wylineſſe of our aduerſaries, that their penned bookes are in euery reſpect learnedly and truly made knowne as they are, to be ouer weake to breake the Walles of Gods church, much leſſe to confounde the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine profeſſed in the ſame. Wherfore, as men alwearied in wofull waſt labors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſundrye conflictes, hauing ſpent all
<pb facs="tcp:226:38"/> their popiſh muniments in this war, they pray a peace, &amp; take a day of truce, and ſo by ſcilence ſubſcribe to the conquering truth, which by his force &amp; their pouertie they are compelled vnto.</p>
            <p>The charged ſhot of treaſon, which the Romaniſtes haue trayled to this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are they not by the Lord, before the time of their diſcharge, and without the ſtrength of man broken al in péeces?<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 54.15.</note> The ſmith that framed them, (the pope I ſay) is he not aſhamed to ſée his Platforme put to foyle? What Nation doth hée more enuie, then this our happye Land? What confederacies doth he make with ſundrie conſpiracies, both wyth in and wyth out the Lande, againſt the Lord<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 2.2</note> and his anoynted Prince? What offers of ayde, what practiſes for proofe of good ſucceſſe, hath his vnholy holineſſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde in this Lande? and yet the Lorde hath deliuered and preſerued from al his ſubtle engines, both her maieſtie and vs, that ſhe ſhould be, (mauger his bearde) the<note n="a" place="margin">Eſa, 49.23</note> Nurſſing Moother, not onely to the Churche vnder her gouernement, but alſo to the Afflicted members of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:226:38"/> CHRIST, which that Huge<note n="b" place="margin">Apo. 12.9</note> Dragon, doth Perſecute from place to place. And happye may her Maieſtie be, that GOD vouchſafeth to ſelect her, (béeing a weake woman) from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the mightie Monarchies of the worlde, to be his choſen nurſe to his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar perſecuted people. So may all we her ſubiectes acknowledge our ſelues more then moſt bound to god for her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, ſince we vnder a mayden Prince, whoſe perſon is vnapt to bodely warres, are ſo defended, that againſt the force of the worlds furie, both our ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are conſerued in much peace, far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the nations rounde about vs. The onely cauſe thereof is Ieſus Chriſt, our mighty<note n="(c)" place="margin">Apo. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Michael,</hi> who himſelf without our fighting hands, or armed bodies, brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth the Dragons force, and diſapointeth him of his pray.</p>
            <p>The ſecond diabolicall imphe, is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical foe which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church harboreth &amp; carieth in her arms, &amp; to quiet &amp; make ſtil his wanton and wrauling cryes, Dand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him on her Mootherly Knée, hoping to ſurpreſſe his brawling voyce wyth
<pb facs="tcp:226:39"/> her patient compaſſion. For ſhew of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, this poyſoned broode calleth her by the name of mother, &amp; her ſpouſe Chriſt, they worſhip by the tittle of Lord. But in déede they are the bond ſlaues of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 4.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>Agar,</hi> and beare a deadly hate to <hi>Sara.</hi> Their mindes be ſet on <hi>Sina</hi> that gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth bondage, <hi>(vz.</hi> rotten <hi>Rome</hi>)<note n="b" place="margin">26.</note> and <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> they ſéeke but to féede vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, to floriſhe in, to enriche themſelues vnder her. And eſpying her<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 2.4.</note> liberties, and preheminences, they doe from time to time buſie themſelues to betray the ſame. The true church of God now in Englande, ſéeke they to betray to the handes of the wicked, and by<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſa. 87.20.</note> ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to polute the ſanctuarie of the Lord. The engines that theſe enemies vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs, are ſcoffing ſpeches, rayling voyces, and ſlaundering wordes. Sée you not ſay theſe men, what diſcorde, ſundry ſectes and religious are amongeſt theſe new broched bretherne, how they preach, wryte, diſpute, and euer ſeeke to beate downe another? Is not this a marke of Sathans Sinagog. And the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of theſe euilles, is to couller their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:226:39"/> cankred malice, with the<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 17.6.7.</note> couert of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired obedience to Lawes, whyleſt ſuch for the moſt parte liue as though they themſelues were priuileadged from all good gouernement. The contempt of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lawes ſet downe in this ſtate and preſent gouernement, is to be wyth dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent eye, and earneſt care redreſſed. And I would to GOD ſuche rulers Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical &amp; ciuill were ſelected as would more diligently looke hereto. So ſhould the mouthes of men haue leſſe cauſe of their great outcryes agaynſt the preſent ſtate. For I thinke it no reaſon to pull downe the whole houſe, for the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of on rotten ſparre, or to cutte of the hande for the fault or defect of a finger, or yet vtterly to ſubuert the ſtate becauſe euery parte hath ſome<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 42.3.</note> infirmitie. But as concerning the contentions amongſt the learned, I anſwere I lament both the cauſe and the action: yet here by hath the papiſt no warrant to Blaſpheme our Religion, or to condemne the Prince or Preachers and profeſſors of the ſame, for if contention amydde the learned and in the Church of God be a ſufficient cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:226:40"/> to refuſe her, to ſlaunder and to reuile her wyth reprochfull tearmes, yea, and condemne the people, ſtate, and miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of chriſts ſpouſed wife this holy church: then ſhall we finde this Churche in no age among the children of men planted, frée from ſuch ſharpe cenſure.</p>
            <p>As if we loke into the church of Iſraell brought from <hi>Pharao</hi> into the deſert, we ſhall ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame often to rebell againſt<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ex. 15.24.17.2.32.1. Nu. 20 2.</note> 
               <hi>Moiſes,</hi> yet not all the Iſraelits. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church then could not be frée from contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Nu. 14.2.</note> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Nu. 16.1.</note> 
               <hi>Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram</hi> diſliking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſthood which god ouer them had ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ex. 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>Aron</hi> his line, ſtirred vp ſharpe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention &amp; tumultuous vprore for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Conſider her condition in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Saule,</hi> his perſecuting of <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; behold ſmall vnitie: <hi>Saule</hi> commended of ſome,<note n="b" place="margin">Sa. 18.7.8</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> reaping the greater praiſe. What vnity had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>400.</hi> ſalſe<note n="c" place="margin">1. King. 18.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, contended with <hi>Helias</hi> the prophet of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idoll Baal their falſe god? After Iſrael retorned from her captiuity was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church cut into diuers ſectes &amp; factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? in outward ſhow they profeſſed gods law penned by<note n="d" place="margin">Io. 9.28.</note> 
               <hi>Moiſes</hi> &amp; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phets: but in déede &amp; truth they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated into diuers opinions &amp; ſundrie
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:226:40"/> ſects. &amp; euery party receiued his name ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The holy ſcripture &amp; approued authors tell vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes church there were <hi>Phariſes, Saduces</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis,</hi> yet who dare ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther was not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gods holy church? It is therfore now, no ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or new thing to haue diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in &amp; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profeſſing one religion, about ſome points conteined in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. The new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t witneſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles what ſharpe contention was there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Paule</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Antioch</hi> for cauſe in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 2.11.12.13.14.</note> rules therof, was openly reproued by <hi>Paule.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo betwixt <hi>Paule</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas</hi> was ſuch v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they parted aſonder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, about<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 15.39.</note> 
               <hi>John Marke</hi> a diſciple. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table is that long &amp; ſharpe diſputation &amp; ſore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention which crept into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, betwixt <hi>Paule</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas</hi> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one part, &amp; the Phariſes which were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell at <hi>Antioch</hi> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, about<note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. 15.1.</note> iuſtification, whether it came by faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or that circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion &amp; the law were of neceſſitie to be ioined thereto. This ſtrife was ſuch, that it could not nor was other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe abandoned the church, then by that
<pb facs="tcp:226:41"/> Apoſtolicall councell holden at Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. About this time, and ſhortly after the Apoſtles there aroſe out of the church ſundry ſectaries, as the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Verſ. lib. 3. c. 28. Illir. cent. 1. lib. 2. c. 5. fol. 481.</note> 
               <hi>Corinthiani,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Eccl. hiſto. lib. 4. c. 11</note> 
               <hi>Martionisti,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Euſ. li. 4 c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Gnostici</hi> and<note n="(g)" place="margin">Euſ. li. 4. c. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratiani.</hi> The Gentilles then as ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes doe now, ſayde the chriſtians are troubleſome and contentious, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agrée about their chriſt and his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but we: holde one vnitie in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, therefore they offer vs more then great cauſe, to haue in ſuſpence our haſt to ſubſcribe to their profeſſed Goſpel. Yet all this their friuolous ſpeches ſet a part, both the Apoſtles and others wyth them at that preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ioyning in the ſinceritie of the profeſſed trueth, were of the true church of God. Alſo that church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe wicked Sectories, &amp; Heritykes came, was that, and the beſt beloued Wyfe the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſuch contentions and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mindes, as then that ſtate caryed to the poſteritie. And euen ſo is our church now holding faſt the ſubſtance of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine geuen by the ſcriptures, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:226:41"/> to his worde. Lykewiſe in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, though in ſome matter accident<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth there ariſe queſtion, the ſame yet offe-no ioy to the profeſſed papiſt for as they contende, ſo doe both ſides ſtriue to be far from popiſh affects. This our Church alſo I ſay, of and in England, is the true church of God, &amp; the reuerend fathers the Biſhops, with others the preachers of his holy word, in this our nation, &amp; now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, abiding in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of doctrine, (though ther be) amids their harmony, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome little iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring crochet in leſſe matters out of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke her concorde, are to be accompted as members of that muſicall body, whereof Chriſt is the head, and worthy<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.10.</note> buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of that ſpirituall houſe of which Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord is the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 2.20.</note> chiefe corner ſtone. If I ſhould ſtand to reherſe the contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church, ſince the firſt Church till this preſent, I ſhould paſſe the limits of a large booke, farſed with onely teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to that end. As for example the contention among the learned and Godly fathers in the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Cent. 2. cap 8.</note> Eaſt and weſt churches. for the time and day: wherein the Eaſter
<pb facs="tcp:226:42"/> day ſhould be kept, was great and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a cutting aſunder of the ſaid church, and an abſolute breache of perfect vnity, till<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibidem. fo. 158.</note> Nicene councell ended the cauſe, but ſalued not the whole ſore. For the hygh authoritye of places and men Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, it is a worlde to reade and ſée how<note n="(c)" place="margin">Epiſt. Gre. lib. 4. Epi. 34.38. E. 78</note> Iohn the Biſhop of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> began, and the Romane Gregory encountering him, Prophecied his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſeate to be prepared for the ſame Antechriſtianiſme after his dayes, which<note n="d" place="margin">Palmerius Veſperius.</note> Boniface the worker of euill enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſed in his full pompe, which contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I feare will not be baniſhed, till the ſpirit of the Lords<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſ. 2.8.</note> mouth conſume y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authors &amp; fautors thereof. This ſore how in thoſe better dayes, &amp; more pure times it hath feſtered into the harts of Godly &amp; learned men, then moſt famous, by this little taſte ye may at the firſt perceiue. But let vs (as ye would haue it, O ye fawning papiſts) graunt ye that ſome Hereſies doe bréed in our Engliſh church at this day, ſhall ye? therefore accuſe the ſame to be eſtraunged from God, ſhall you wyth wylye ſubtletie (to that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:226:42"/> ye may) deface the Churche our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Moother, and carye the names of her Sonnes and Children, and louers of our gracious Nurſe, ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH? Naye, rather ought ye to lyke of our Religion that manifeſteth ſuche Hereſies, and confeſſe that where the Lorde hath fyrſt ſowne Wheate, there the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 13.24.25.</note> Enemie comming after, hath in the ſame choſen Lande ſowed Tares. And ye ought to know that the Lordes will is, to haue<note n="b" place="margin">Verſ. 30.</note> both for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to grow together, that the blade of the Tare might the better make knowne the eare of the good wheat. So is it (good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſdome of Gods purpoſe, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies ſpringing vp with true doctrine, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veritie ſhould more clearly appeare, and the ſowers of truth ſhould more diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtudy to refell the falſe opinions of the wicked, by the forcible power of that firſt ſowne<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 13.19. Mark. 4.14 Luk. 8.11.</note> truth, the word of God. Let not the wicked therefore perſwade thée that our Church and Religion is euill &amp; falſe, becauſe of ſciſmes &amp; Hereſies which ſome wicked, not yet by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church fully cut of, percaſe do hold, for it bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:226:43"/> Apoſtles time, that Heritykes and Seiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matykes ſhould fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true church haue their procéedinge, and of the ſame their firſt place to be<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Io. 2.10. Act. 15.24.</note> trayned vp in trueth, that their Iudgement ſhould be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, (which is now wrapped in horrible hereſie, and manifold ſciſmes, though they yet boaſt of vnitie) came out of Gods church, and hath made manifeſt Apoſtacie there from: as if you ſet the Religion in Rome now profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, wyth the Doctrine which the ſame dyd holde what tyme <hi>Paule</hi> wrot his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to them, you ſhall moſt playnely ſée, that the Romaniſtes are gone out of Gods Churche great and Huge He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityques. Came not <hi>Arius,</hi> that peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous man (who hath by his Bookes denyed Chriſtes Eternitie wyth the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Euſ. lib. ecl. hi. li. 7. cap. 10.</note> Father, onely acknowledging him to be made as a Creature. (Oh myghty and Monſtrous Blaſphemie) came he not out I ſay of the Churche of GOD at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where he was firſt a Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter and after an admitted Preacher? dyd he not of malice,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Trip. hi. li. 10. c. 12.</note> agaynſt <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the good Biſhop, there firſt broche
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:226:43"/> forth his Hereſies. Where had <hi>Agelius;<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> his place to ſpred his Hereſie (which was of the ſect of <hi>Nouatus</hi> that Heretike, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vp in the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> and was the Father of the Heretykes,<note place="margin">Euſ. lib. 6. cap. 34.</note> called <hi>Katharoi</hi>) but euen where the chriſtian <hi>Chriſostom</hi> was chiefe Paſtour and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and in his Church at <hi>Constantinople?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trip. lib. 5 cap. 32.</note> Shall the contentions in the Apoſtles age, in Chriſtes Church then, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies amongeſt the learned in the Chriſtian Churches ſince, cut the one or the other? from being the Church of God? God forbid. Yea, if from the church of the Apoſtles there procéeded ſciſmes &amp; Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies by the wicked amongſt them, if ſince in all times, as the Eccl. hiſtories tell vs, Satan hath ſo troubled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good corne with counterfait cockle, why ſhal we thinke it ſtrange to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame tentations now, which our fathers before vs, &amp; our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after our departure, ſhalbe aſſalted with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea your holy mother of <hi>Rome</hi> (ye papiſts) hath nurſed vp ſuch wicked children her ſelfe (in whom &amp; whoſe popes alone, ye re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe your whole truſt) as may bear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bel, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill the patron of your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for their great hereſies. And they are
<pb facs="tcp:226:44"/> ſundry in number. As <hi>Liberius. Anastati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Honorius, Siluester,</hi> and the mery mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iohn, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> B. aboue others more nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Adhere to al the reſt in that ſea, ſince Antechriſts poſſeſſion firſt thereof taken. Albeit ye cannot deny the premiſes, or kéep fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſight your many &amp; ſundry iar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yet ye wold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſinagog of Rome, ſhould be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted the holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch &amp; mother church of the world, &amp; that notwithſtanding the procreation of ſuch a peſtilent &amp; poyſoning brood: why ſhould ye then abridge vs, of the lyke libertie which ye chalenge to your ſelues, &amp; that ſéeing we doe with all might ſéeke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preffe the opinions of them that be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wyth the power of the Goſpell, and to mayneteyne vnitye in Godlyneſſe, to all our powers. Herein you doe but poure out your much malice &amp; ſtriuing to hinder vs. You haue exhibited againſt your willes, much lyke to your graund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 11.50</note> 
               <hi>Caiphas,</hi> to our ſide, and with vs, the Teſtimonye of trueth. So mightie is God our defender, that he draweth wyth violence out of your wicked mouthes, to your greater condemnation if ye repent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:226:44"/> not, the vouch of verity. But to conclude this poynt (Chriſtian reader) take and taſte this <hi>Antidotum,</hi> here confected to thy vſe, agaynſt their venomous ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and it ſhall not onely comfort thy afflicted minde, (which God graunt for his Sonnes ſake,) but alſo ſhall kéepe thée ſtedfaſt, vntill the Lorde performe the promiſe, long ſyth by his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes ſolempnely made to his Churche for euer. As firſt in <hi>Micah</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah. 7.20</note> thus. Thou wylt perfourme thy trueth to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and mercye to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as thou haſte Sworne to our Fathers in olde tyme.<note place="margin">Eſa. 54.11.12.</note> And agayne in <hi>Eſay</hi> wholy and ſpecially from eleuenth verſe to the ende of the ſame, which Chapter is moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble agaynſt theſe our ſubtill dayes.<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> Oh thou afflicted and toſſed wyth Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes (ſayth the Prophete to Goddes Churche) thou that haſt no comfort: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I wil lay thy ſtones with <hi>Carbuncle,</hi> &amp; lay thy foundations w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Saphire,</hi> &amp; I wil make thy windows of <hi>Emraudes,</hi> &amp; thy gates ſhining ſtones, &amp; all thy borders of pleaſant ſtones, and all thy Children ſhal be taught of God, and much peace ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:226:45"/> vnto thy Children, in righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed and be farre from oppreſſion, for thou ſhalt not feare it, and from feare, for it ſhall not come nie thée. Beholde the Enemye ſhall gather himſelfe, but wythout me, whoſoeuer ſhall gather hymſelfe in thée, agaynſt thée ſhall fall. Beholde, I haue made the Smyth, that bloweth the Coales in the Fyre, and him that bringeth forth an Inſtrument for his worke, and I haue Created the Deſtroyer to deſtroy, but all the Weapons that are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thée, ſhall not proſper. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Tongue that ſhall aryſe vp againſt thée in Iudgement, thou ſhalt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne. Thys is the Lordes Heritage and their ryghteouſneſſe is of mée ſayth the LORDE. Thus farre the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete ſpeaketh, to teache thée (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) great cauſe of comfort and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage agaynſt diſpayre, though England, which is Gods church, haue now many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies riſen vp againſt her, &amp; her religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea, though her owne ſkirtes doe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſuche as inſult agaynſt her, ſhe is Promiſed that theyr Weapons and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:226:45"/> the ſmith that framed them ſhal not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper. Their lybelling bookes which ſéeke to perſecute her, though they come from the houſe of counſell, and ſéeme to procede from the ſeate of learnings iudgement, yet ſhal this church of God be ſet a Iudge ouer their wearie trauels and toyling ſpite, and ſhall condemne them.</p>
            <p>Let that worthy <hi>Jewel</hi> of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the holy confeſſor and Saint of and by Ieſus Chriſt, treaſured vp in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pydarie of the heauens for the glory of our God, let his excellent workes (I ſay) ſtand for an ample warrant hereto, to this age &amp; to her poſteritie for euer. And let others whether at home or abroade looke for the ſame end of their moleſting troubles, which they caſt into this our age and Church. But thou wilt ſay, why doth the Lord ſuffer ſo long our weake conſciences to be troubled with theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſtrifes? What art thou (O man) that wilt diſpute with God? Theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to vs yet in reſpect of the Schiſmes of old, are but as an entring into the firſt moment of the day. Waite thou the lords leyſure and be ſtill, learne thy ſong fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:226:46"/> by firme hope in truth, which <hi>Micah</hi> hath taught the church of God, alwayes in her trouble to ſing, &amp; thou ſhalt be relie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued though thy enemies yet ſéeke to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer thée.<note place="margin">Micah. 7.8</note> 
               <hi>Reioyce not againſt me, O my enemie,</hi> (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church there) for though I fal, I ſhal ariſe, when I ſhal ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the Lord ſhall be a light vnto me, I will beare the wrath of the Lord, becauſe I haue ſinned againſt him, vntil he plead my cauſe and execute iudgement for me, then wil he bring me forth to the light, &amp; I ſhal ſée his righteouſnes. Then ſhe that is my enemie ſhall looke vpon it, &amp; ſhame ſhall couer her, which ſaid vnto me, <hi>Where is the Lord thy God?</hi> my eyes ſhall behold her, now ſhal ſhe be troden downe as the myre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtréets. &amp;c. Thus much forth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet <hi>Micah,</hi> where thou maiſt learn to accuſe thy ſelf for thy ſinne, as<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. Sa. 24.17</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> did, ſéeing the people afflicted, &amp; not with<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Re. 18.17</note> 
               <hi>Achab</hi> to charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, or his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; Prophets, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> troubles &amp; plagues ariſe in the church, but to turne thy eyes into thy owne conſcience, &amp; ſée the booke of thy iniquities there written, &amp; to confeſſe before god &amp; man, that thy ſinne is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:226:46"/> of ſuch trouble &amp; plague brought into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; people by Satan his malice, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pollicie of theſe his wicked impes. Laſt of all, diſcourage not at the romiſh ſcoffes &amp; taunting reproches, nor yet deſpaire in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottome of her darke dungeons, &amp; ſharpe perſecutions, for the lord wil comfort thée in them, if thou reſt vpon his layſure, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine conſtant, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end deliuering thée wil ſtampe thy enemie into dirt, &amp; make thée beautiful in the ſight of al men, that thou maiſt ſerue him thy god, thus deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feare, in new holines deuoid of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, in iuſtice &amp; righteous dealing, to, &amp; with al men, in the place of thy abode &amp; traffike els where amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt men in earth. And euer reſpect thy deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, &amp; regard thy ſtate ſo, that Satan eftſones pul thée not to thy former ſinne, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth his erſt bondage, for the end of ſuch as ſo fal, is worſe then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning. And thus much for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt part of this Hymne, in which I haue bene more prolixe then firſt I purpoſed, but I truſt that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite which may riſe vppon the attentiue reading of the matter ſimply ſet downe, wil cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teruaile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tedious ſight of ſo much blotted paper, ſith my willing trauayles
<pb facs="tcp:226:47"/> hath forced me to dwell in comfortable ſpéech with the leſſe learned, ſome thing the longer, becauſe they of themſelues can not conceiue ſuch profitable matter, as this our text doth exhibite to the ſerching eye: aſſuredly perſwaded that the better (ſo godly) learned will vouchſafe ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Cenſure</hi> to this my vnpoliſhed pen. And wherein I erre from the truth, if by the ſame I may heare louingly therof, as I hope I haue geuen no poyſon to the Church, ſo I wilbe glad to reforme that and thoſe thinges which godly reaſons with learned truth ſhall require at my hands. The Lord graunt continuance of his goſpell in this Nation, preſeruation to her Maieſtie, with encreaſe of Gods knowledge, and zeale to his holy name, and to vs and his whole Church, from all hereſies, Sciſmes, and ciuill diſſentions, if it ſtand with his good wil and pleaſure, once full deliuerance, that we may ſerue the Lord our god in ſinceritie of hart, and integritie of life in his ſight, by his holy ſpirite all the dayes of our life, to whom, by and with Chriſt our Lord, to that dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the trinal vnitie, be al praiſe power &amp; glory for euer. Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:226:47"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> And thou child ſhalt be called the Prophet of the most high, for thou ſhalt goe before the face of the Lord, to prepare his wayes.</q>
            <p>As the ſacred Prieſt before had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gods great benefites and faithfulnes in performing his louing promiſes, to the redemption of his elect: So now he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to this preſent action, and vſing the perſon of an interpreter expoundeth the Oracle of God, declaring his ſonne this child, to be the ſame preacher and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, which erſt by the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> was promiſed<note n="(a)" place="margin">Malach. 3.1 Eſa. 4.3</note> to precede Chriſt. By whoſe trauel in Doctrine, the way ſhould be prepared for the Lordes comming, his and our <hi>Meſsias.</hi> Which office this babe in his appoynted time executed right wel with ſinceritie of hart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſparing no perſon, place, time, or people, or omitted any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when he might moſt aptly performe ſuch his calling. This Baptiſtes voyce
<pb facs="tcp:226:48"/> was euer crying againſt the ſinnes of all, exhibiting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedie for that horrible gilt to as many as aproched his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he could ſend forth his heroical voice crying:<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 3.1</note> 
               <hi>Repent for the kingdome of god is at hand.</hi> In theſe <hi>.2.</hi> verſes we haue as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conſider y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſugred ſence, &amp; comforta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble doctrine which in them is contained.</p>
            <p>And firſt as touching the ſpéech of Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie to his little babe, note the mercy of God to Zacharie himſelfe, for albeit hée returned incredible ſpéech, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angel, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>How ſhal J know</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Luc. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>this, for J am old, &amp; my wife is of great age.</hi> Yet god cauſed the Angel to procede in his meſſage, &amp; correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his incredulitie ſaid,<note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 1.19</note> I am <hi>Gabriel,</hi> that ſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of god, &amp; am ſent to ſpeake to thée, &amp; to ſhew thée theſe good tidings, and behold thou ſhalt be dumbe &amp; not be able to ſpeak vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day that theſe things be done, bicauſe thou beleuedſt not my words, which ſhalbe fulfilled in their ſeaſon. A notable example of gods mercy &amp; iuſtice<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 101.1 &amp; 85.10.</note> met togither in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of this holy prieſt. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he refuſed to giue cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dit to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching <hi>Gabriel,</hi> Gods iuſtice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertoke his ſinne, &amp; proclaymed his gilt, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Cenſure</hi> of his iudgement in the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:226:48"/> mouth, which preſently tooke effect in him. For he comming forth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, was ſéene not able to ſpeak, but made ſignes<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luc. 1.22</note> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, &amp; ſo remained till y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame mercifull God by his holy ſpirit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his mouth, to vouch his praiſe by this Prophetical Hymne. Whereout wée rightly gather his ineſtimable mercy, meaſured by his loue, which could not be cut ſhort of his purpoſe, by<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 3.3.4.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malice of Zacharies ſin, or wold depriue this holy man of ſo great a benefite, though his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſinne deſerued it. And is this done for him alone? No: for vs alſo that beleue in Chriſt Ieſus, to vs is god the one &amp; ſame that here he was to Zacharie. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is Zacharies ſinnes<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. Sa. 11.4.13.15.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,<note n="b" place="margin">Ionas. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Jonas</hi> gilt<note n="(c)" place="margin">Exo. 32.2</note> 
               <hi>Aaron</hi> his fal,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iere. 20.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremies</hi> heate,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 26.65.</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> denial,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Luc. 7.32</note> 
               <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalens</hi> vice<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. 20.21.</note> 
               <hi>Zebedes</hi> ſonnes with their ambition, ſet down to the church in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might haue hope &amp; conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſo often as we imitate into their maners, &amp; take ſuruey of gods iuſtice, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mercy vnto theſe &amp; others the godly fathers. For he accepting not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of fleſh, but in all places,<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer calleth vppon his name ſhalbe ſaued,
<pb facs="tcp:226:49"/> from their ſinnes of what condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be. To all the elect of God it is ſaid,<note n="(i(" place="margin">Eſa. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>Jf your ſinnes were as red as Scarlet, J will make them as white as Wooll.</hi> No one of thoſe are excluded from this comfort,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 11.28</note> 
               <hi>Come to me all you that trauell, and bee heauie laden, and J will refreſh you.</hi> Aſſured of this, alſo ſhall all the elect of God be, that in whom there remayneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> canker of ſinne (as it doth in all corrupted fleſh) in them the mercifull iuſtice of God ſhall by his<note n="(l)" place="margin">2. Sa. 24.16.</note> ſtriking Angell, be found to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their ſinne. For he ſcourgeth euery<note n="(m)" place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> ſonne that hée receiueth: Hée ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times chaſteneth with the ſcourge of<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32</note> naturall death his beloued, that their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie ſhould not caſt them with the<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32</note> reprobate into eternal fire. And in whom can be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his quickning ſpirit, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their killing<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ro. 8.13.</note> fleſh, in them his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hand is euer exerciſed to<note n="(d)" place="margin">Io. 14.2</note> purge their ſinne, and force more fruite. But here note with me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hate which god doth beare to the<note n="(e)" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.6 Pſal. 82.5.6</note> diſcredit of his word, vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the teachers of his truth. He ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not to plague the ſame in his<note n="(f)" place="margin">Eſa. 28.12.15.16.19.20 Marc. 6.</note> holy ones, yea, be they neuer ſo neceſſary mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:226:49"/> and helpes to his Church.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luc. 1.20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Rather ſhould all <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> be deſtitute of their preaching Prophet, and their ſacrifiſing prieſt Zacharie, then god would ſpare to chaſtiſe the doubtfull hearing of his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute word. Where note, he more requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth an obedient eare to his truth,<note n="(f)" place="margin">1. Sa. 13.9.10.11.12.13.14.15. &amp; 15.3.9.19.28.</note> then al painful toyl in wilworſhip, or ſacrifices by him ſelfe els commaunded. What ſhal then the obſtinate &amp; rebellious Papiſtes, the heritiques of our age doe, that flatly contemne the ſame? Truely this is the Cenſure of God againſt them<note n="(g)" place="margin">Prou. 1.24.</note> I haue called (ſaith the Lord) &amp; ye haue refuſed, I haue ſtretched out mine hand, and none would regard, but ye haue deſpiſed al my counſell, and would none of my correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will alſo laugh at your deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and mocke when your feare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth like ſoddaine deſolation: and your deſtruction ſhall come like a whyrle wind, when affliction and anguiſh ſhall come vpon you. Then ſhal they cal vpon me, but I wil not anſwere, they ſhal ſéek me early but they ſhall not find me, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hated knowledge &amp; did not chuſe the feare of the lord. They would none of my
<pb facs="tcp:226:50"/> counſell, but despiſed al my correction. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhal they eate of the fruite of their owne way, and be filled with their owne deuiſes: for eaſe ſlaieth the fooliſh, and the proſperitie of fooles deſtroyeth them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But he that obeyeth me ſhal dwel ſafely, and be quiet from feare of euil.</hi> Secondly we may perceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riches of gods mercy, who doth not only forgiue Zacharies ſinne, but enritcheth him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a moſt ſpeciall gift of prophecie, that no man ſhould diſpayre to do well, becauſe erſt he hath bene euill, or that any ſhould denie all them apt to the function of God, which tofore haue bene inobedient, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious to his word. No: meaſure not the man by that he was, but accept him to that he now is made by the grace of God<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 2.7.8.9.10.</note> powred into him: And be not thou ſeuere, where God is ſoueraigne. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon for thoſe euils, which the lords mercy hath not only pardoned, but alſo hath &amp; doth endowe with freſh &amp; more bountifull giftes then erſt hée had, or poſſible, ſome others which malice ſuch men, can make apparant to dwel in them ſelues. Idolatrie no dout is an huge ſinne, but is not infidelitie the mother thereof?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:226:50"/> And incredulitie a beame of that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.2.3.4.5.6.7.8 9.10.11.27.28</note> yet from infidelitie God calleth to his Chriſt. Yea ſuch as haue bene nurſed vp in Idolatrie, to his ſeruice. And the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>credulous to the preaching of faith. In whom we ſée this ſimple conuerſion, let vs acknowledge it for<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 9.26.27.</note> gods worke, and do not ſéeke to apall the place, &amp; credite of ſuch, but rather aſſiſt (yea to the face of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle, and gouernours in the church) them, &amp; euery of them, to whom the Lord hath made himſelfe knowne, &amp; hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to their hartes ſo, that they by his grace (with <hi>Paul</hi>) haue ſéene the Lord in their paſſage, &amp; embaſing themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, haue confeſſed him to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, &amp; boldly do vouch him tofore kings &amp; men. Know wel this, that at what time<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ezec. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the wicked part from their ill, their ſinnes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord putteth quite out of his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance. Now as of Zacharies perſon hitherto we haue beſtowed the vew of gods mercy towards him: So let vs conſider now his propheticall wordes, to, &amp; concerning the purpoſe of God in this Baptiſt. Thus he ſaith: <hi>And thou little babe ſhalt be called the Prophet of the highest. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:226:51"/>
            <p>By theſe words we are put in mind ſtil of Gods aboundant mercy, in his Chriſt, who not only maketh Zacharie an old &amp; comfortable father: but openeth alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the arcane counſel of his diuine diſpoſition. And by the ſpirit of prophecy, aſſureth him and the Church committed to him of the heauenly benefite, their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deliuerance in this Chriſt their true <hi>Meſsias,</hi> of whom this little babe that yet can nothing ſay ſhalbe the moſt noble preacher and Prophet. When hée calleth him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords Prophet, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledgeth him to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> interpreter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords Law and Oracles, the Doctor and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in &amp; to the Church of God, by whoſe mouth the Lord him ſelfe ſpeaketh to the ſame, opening to them his ſecretes, and manifeſting his holy will, as appeareth by that which followeth: <hi>To geue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Saluation. &amp;c.</hi> Which prophecie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father was fulfilled in his ſonne the Baptiſt, in the the firſt yeare of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> at which time Chriſt was about thirtie yeres of age.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 3.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>And John began to preach publiquely ſaying, Repent for the kingdome of God is at hand.</hi> Two notable thinges in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:226:51"/> the wordes of this his text he promiſeth to his ſonne, by his warrant receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. Firſt that albeit he be in reſpect of natures worke, and the worldes reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a ſmall child, and of lowe degrée, yet hath the lord choſen &amp; appointed him from his cradell: nay, before his creation<note n="(b)" place="margin">Luc. 1.13.</note> to be the inſtrument moſt apt to the Lordes labour. The ſecond is the nature of his office, which is to prepare &amp; make<note n="(a)" place="margin">Luc. 1.16.17 18.19.</note> ſtraight the way of the Lord, as the Angel before had ſayd to Zacharie in the viſion. Who being corrected for his dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes aſſured him ſelfe, and others, moſt conſtantly of the Lordes promiſe, which was, that this holy Prophet the Baptiſt ſhould be great in the ſight of God, and ſhould not geue him ſelfe with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Prieſtes of the earth, or the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of Iſrael, to gorge their crawes with bibbing cheare, but ſhould lead an auſtere &amp; temperate diet, hauing his hart wholy ſet vpon his office, which the ſpirit of God ſelected him to from his mothers wombe,<note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 1.16.</note> that he ſhould turne the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael to their Lord God, by that heroicall ſpirite, which God erſt gaue to
<pb facs="tcp:226:52"/> 
               <hi>Helias:</hi> to turne the harts of the fathers to the children, and the diſobedient to the wiſedome of the iuſt men, to make ready a people, prepared for the lord. This was the moſt excellent office of the Baptiſt, in conſideration wherof this Zachary ſong this <hi>Pſalme</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords praiſe. Now let vs note here (good reader) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but by gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce al things are guided to his glory &amp; the churches profite. Not any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſet into place, autoritie, or any office, but are appointed of god in his wiſdome, yea before they are to be men<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 44.28 Exo. 2.2. &amp; 3.5.10. &amp; 4.27. &amp; 28.1.2. 1. Sa. 9.1.15. cap. 16.1.12.13. ca. 3.4. Amos 7.14 15. Iere. 1.5. Eſa. 1.1 Heb. 5.5.6 Gal. 1.15. Mat. 10. &amp;c</note> &amp; beyond his ſearch, ſute, or expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of his god. As <hi>Moyſes, Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Saul Dauid, Samuel, Amos, Jeremie, Eſay,</hi> Chriſt him ſelfe, <hi>Paule,</hi> the Apoſtles els, and all others before and ſince. The very wicked Magiſtrates their office and authoritie is of the Lord,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Prou. 8.15.</note> by him kinges doe raigne good or euil. In that they are kinges<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1</note> of his good wiſedome it is, but as they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill<note place="margin">VViſd. 6.4 7.19.3.1 1. Pet. 3.13</note> it is of their owne frowardnes &amp; Satans malice, from which perſons ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may the action of Gods iuſtice in any wiſe be ſeperate. <hi>Pharao</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Exo. 14.4.8</note> his hart the Lord hardened, <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">2. L. 24.1.2.3. &amp;. 20.17. &amp; 33.27</note> hée
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:226:52"/> ſtirred vp againſt the children of Iſrael. <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herode</hi> with the Gentiles and cruel <hi>Jewes</hi> were in their malicious harts furiouſly bent, and did in déede gather them ſelues together againſt Chriſt the annoynted of the Lord. But it<note n="(g)" place="margin">Act. 4.24.25.26.27.28 29.30</note> was to do whatſoeuer the hand and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Lord had before determined to be done. All which emphatically Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie voucheth vnder this word <hi>(Thou ſhalt &amp;c.)</hi> Wherefore let vs depend vpon our heauenly fathers prouidence, and what gouernement, raigne, pollicie, or order ſo euer we ſée, prayſe God for the good, pray God to amend, rectifie or remoue the euill at his good pleaſure, and for his ſpirit to direct our ſteppes, knowing that as a ſparowe falleth not to the ground without the heauenly fathers prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, So ſhall nothing come to paſſe without his good pleaſure to his elect. And the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſhall euer be to them (becauſe they feare the Lord), good and proſperous. Oh that ye Papiſtes, <hi>Atheists,</hi> and other the Macheuils of this our age, could conſider this then would ye not ſo range at the Goſpell, or ſo enuie the profeſſors
<pb facs="tcp:226:53"/> therof, or yet conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſo gracious gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as is ſet ouer you &amp; vs, by the which (not by caſualitie, but by diuine deſtinie) gods word is ſo amplie preached, &amp; forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beaten into your eares, that were you not<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.8.</note> appointed to the ſlaughter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of wrath, impoſſible ſhould it be for you to remayne rebellious. But ſo is it Gods good pleaſure to rayſe vp little Baptiſts, and lowly babes to poſſeſſe that grace<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 11.25. Luc. 10.21</note> which you wiſe and mightie Giants of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world deſpiſe and perſecute. All prayſe be to thée O heauenly father therefore, and continually vouchſafe thy bleſſing to this our nation, graunt our <hi>Dauid</hi> to conſider thy choyſe of her Maieſtie, which was not from the fold of ſimple ſhepe, but out of the Lions téeth the Papiſts clawes, out of the Towers priſon, and tirans death, to féede thy people of England, in the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 78.70.</note> ſinceritie of her harte, and the porcion of her gracious giftes beſtowed vppon her. Moreouer, I note to thée (good reader) the yet more mercie of our good GOD, who ſpilleth not, but ſpareth the worlde for the electes ſake, and before he ſendeth deſtruction for ſinne, he exhibiteth to that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:226:53"/> people his Prophetes, to call them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ioel. 2.14. Ier 18.8.</note> that he in lyke ſort, may torne from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil which he hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned agaynſt them. As to <hi>Adam</hi> in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> he appeared by him ſelfe. To<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ex. 3.4.5.6 7.</note> 
               <hi>Cain</hi> by his voyce from heauen. To <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ex. 3.4.5.6 7.</note> by <hi>Mosſes.</hi> To <hi>Achab</hi> &amp; his age<note n="(e)" place="margin">1. K. 17.1.2.</note> by <hi>Hely.</hi> To the Iewes before the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion by <hi>Eſay. Je.</hi> &amp; ſundry others. To Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ma. 3. Ioh. 1.</note> by Iohn Baptiſt. Chriſt Ieſus and his Apoſtles, forty and od yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, and all to call theſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and true turning to the Lorde, by the warning of the Trumpe of God, the mouthes of the Preachers. But alas, theſe ages as they are paſt before vs, ſo haue they left to their poſteritie, as yet, their former vices of ſecuritie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the preachers voyce. So that <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> may well ſay at this houre<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 53.1.</note> Lorde who beleueth our ſaying? or to whom is the arme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord knowne? But woe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertooke them, and ſo ſhall it all ſuch as deſpiſing the light of the worde,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 3.19.</note> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſtill in the myre of mans deuiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt God. Where God offereth his worde, therewyth he ſheweth himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:226:54"/> bent to mercie. But if both he ſpare to ſtrike, and ſpende his holy labors by his Propheticall preachers in vaine, to the people to whom he ſendeth them: then and there will he poure out his double plagues to their vtter confuſion. Let <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> alone ſuffize to teſtifye the ſame. And grant (O Lord, more grace to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we in no ſort receue this thy long ſuffering &amp; aboundant gracious light of thy bleſſed truth in vaine, for thy ſonnes ſake. For then aſſuredly, as it now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by thy handy work, &amp; is become to be the beſt <hi>Receptacle,</hi> for thy afflicted members: So ſhall it then be ſene, an horrible Cage for euery foule byrde, and fylthie gryppe, and in ſtede of ſonges of mirth and ioy, howling, lamentation and mourning: for her great deſolation ſhall found her ſorow to the heauens, &amp; redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the earth againe, accompanied wyth thy moſt terrible plagues, in vehement ſort. Oh the ſecuritie of England. Oh, the manifeſt contempt of the Engliſh nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Oh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe diſſimulation that enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borders of this land, as no wher thence, it were permitted to haue his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:226:54"/> Wel: God ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to thée, yet once <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> &amp; Iohn Bap. in plentiful ſort, to cry w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> exalted voice inceſſantly, repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the day of the Lord is at hand. And through the preaching of truth they open the way to ſaluation in Chriſt. Happie be thou, ye twiſe bleſſed, oh miſerable England, canſt thou in time lende thyne Eares, and laye thy hearte to the touche of truethe in this the daye of thy moſte lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing viſitation. And thy day of appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, canſt be readye to tourne to thy Lorde, who ſhall purge thée lyke vnto moſte pure<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mala. 3.3.</note> Syluer. But if the Lorde take from thée (Oh Englande) his Worde and Preaching, then Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is imminent. For when Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fayleth, the people periſhe and dye for want of their ſpiritual breade, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 4.4</note> of their lyfe. Where is the beautie of the former Hieruſalem? What is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Learned <hi>Chorinth,</hi> the pryde of all <hi>Achaia?</hi> And where is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer glory of that Chriſtian <hi>Antioche?</hi> Is not the eaſt Churche wholy become an Apoſtata from God, and them ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruitude of ſinne, &amp; his huge
<pb facs="tcp:226:55"/> enemies? And what ſhal we ſay of that ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Rome, which ſomtime was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deare church of God, is ſhe not now become the ſeate of Antechriſt, and the Sinagogue of Sathan? Yes forſooth. Whence flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Floudes of Godlineſſe, thence commeth the Waters of fylth, in the ſtreame of Idolatrie, ſuperſtition, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, homicide, treaſon, murder, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſinnes agaynſt nature, and the holy Ghoſt. There as in a mirrour, we may ſée the teſtimonie of <hi>Paule</hi> (ſpeaking of the Heathen Idolators) to the Godly <hi>Romanes,</hi> verifyed. For when they<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 22.23.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed themſelues to be wiſe, they became fooles, turning the glory of the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible God, to the ſimilitude of a corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, &amp;c. Wherefore God gaue them vp alſo to their hartes luſtes, vnto vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clearneſſe, to defyle their owne bodies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene themſelues, which tourned the trueth of God to a lye, and worſhipped and ſerued the Creature, forſaking the Creator, which is bleſſed for euer. Amen. For this cauſe ſayth <hi>Paule,</hi> God gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp vnto vile affections. The ſpirit of god foreſeeing the lyke Idolatry and ſinne to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:226:55"/> followe in this ſatanicall Sea, warned them by theſe former plagues to auoyde the ſeconde deſtruction, ſet downe by Iohn the diuine in the Reuelation<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apoc. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 17.8.18.2.</note> But ſith this ſeate is ſet for Antechriſt, and that no man can ſafely vnder her harbor, be ſure from Gods wrath, or can be permitted to nuſſle (as the Sowe) in the myery puddles of her<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ier. 2.13.</note> broken Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes. Let vs wyth on conſent, recoyle to the commaundement of the Spirite, which ſoundeth the retire from Romiſh Babilon, and her damnable deſolation, leſt running in her chaſe, we be ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Lorde, which perſecuteth her. wyth <hi>al arma</hi> of ſundry and ſodeyne Fyghtes to her moſt terrible ouerthrow. And always haue before thine eyes that pyller of Salt, which ſometime was<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 19.26. Luk. 17.32.</note> the holy Lots wife, who for her great loue ſhe bare to her line &amp; bloud, which would not lende their eares to God, receiued a monſtrous ſhape, and loſt the beutie of her firſt Creation: A notable example certaynely.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:226:56"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>10</label> And to giue knowledge of ſaluation vnto his people, by remiſſion of their ſinnes.</q>
            <p>The office of Iohn, and how he is to prepare the way of the Lorde, is here by <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſet downe: namely by the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 3.5.6.7.8.9.10.</note> repentance, and driuing the Iews to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> view of their ſins, wherby they might be the more apt to receiue Chriſt by fayth, &amp; in him ſaluation for their ſins, true righteouſnes &amp; eternall lyfe. This preparation is ſo requiſite, as without the ſame, neither ſhall the wounded man féele his griefe, or the dreined conſcience gaſpe &amp; thirſt after chriſtes bloud, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine of health to euery dry ſinning ſoule, &amp; pined ſinner, that hungreth his water of life. Wherfore his ineſtimable merit hath not onely giuen a ſauiour, but hath ſent a heauenly voyce, to cry out to our deade &amp; deafe bodies, the knowledge of life and way to ſaluation which commeth to vs, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forgeuenes of our ſinnes, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of our good God &amp; moſt merciful father, he hauing fully ſatiſfyed his iuſtice, in the perſon of our crucifyed Chriſt, the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:226:56"/>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſa. 53.</note> chaſtiſement of our peace.</p>
            <p>Thrée eſpeciall poyntes this verſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth: firſt by what means ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is atteined, euen by the forgeuenes of ſins.</p>
            <p>Secondly whoſe ſinnes are forgeuen: Onely the ſinnes of Gods elect &amp; choſen people. Thirdly the way by the which they atteine to ſo hie a price. Euen by that they haue this ſaluation made ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to them by the miniſtery of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that they apprehende by fayth, Gods ſpirit opening the hart of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. Concerning the firſt whence new iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is had, is apparantly ſene by our Prophet, namely that their ſinnes be forgiuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Neither is there in any one to purchaſe ſuch remiſſion, for then ſhould not our iuſtification ſtand in forgiuenes, but in mans purchaſe, &amp; ſo god in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing life ſhould not giue vs his ſon, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording our merit, and his debt, pay to vs chriſt our deſert, which were to vttermoſt peſtilent blaſphemy againſt God and his<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 3.</note> Goſpell. So God loued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world (ſayth Chriſt) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gaue his only begoten ſonne. &amp;c. But this verſe teacheth vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is had by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remiſſion of ſins &amp; ſeteth
<pb facs="tcp:226:57"/> downe both the meane for vs to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende lyfe, and the cauſe of lyfe alſo. The meane or hande whereby we take holde of chriſt which is our lyfe is fayth,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.17.20.</note> noriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bred in our hartes by the worde preached,<note place="margin">Ro. 10.</note> which accepteth chriſt as of the Father he is giuen, and by the ſcriptures he is<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> diſcribed vnto vs. The cauſe here expreſſed is gods loue, who hath predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to lyfe, all thoſe whom he hath tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated from the poynte of death<note n="(c)" place="margin">Col. 1.13.14.15.</note> to the kingdome of his deare ſonne, and from among the wicked of the earth hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, and according to his good will being before<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph. 1.2.3.</note> the foundation of the worlde was layde, hath choſen them to be his people. This is the minde of our Prophet, ſaying. <hi>To giue knowledge. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we ſhould aſke of the Papiſtes, whereby we apprehend Saluation? they will ſay to vs, partly by chriſt, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the worthineſſe of mans workes. Such blaſphemies they bray out of their helly hartes. But (deare reader) be not deceiued by their deluſions, lend thy ſelfe ſome leaſure, to take view for thy wealth of that which here is ſayd. Were it that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:226:57"/> ſaluation could be atteyned by the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of the law (as true it is, the law of-God ſayth<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 2.13.10.6.7.8.</note> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth fulfill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, ſhall lyue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law) yet are there two abſolute reaſones, ouerthrowing all meritte in man, what, or whoſoeuer by the Lawe. The firſte is the impoſſibilytie, that is, men to perfourme the Law. The other is the frayltie of man, which fulfylling (if he could) yet can not alwayes ſtand frée from tranſgreſſing the Law of God. And at what time he falleth, his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes tombleth downe with himſelfe in to the dyche, and ſo fruſtrate is his vaine truſt, before repoſed in his owne holines. For the firſt, he that ſhall by the works of the Lawe become iuſt before God, muſt in hearte be pure from Sinne, for as out of a filthy puddle can naturally come no ſwéete water, ſo out of a wicked hart can procéede no pure action, nor is God pacified from wrath by any worke which procéedeth from a ſinfull and a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſcience. Search &amp; ſeeke from eaſt to weſt, north &amp; ſouth, among the ſonnes of men, &amp; behold, no where ſhalt thou find a man whoſe hart is pure<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pro. 20.9</note> from ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:226:58"/> Nay,<note place="margin">1. Io. 1. 2. Cro. 6.36 1. d. 8.46.</note> whoſe harte is not altogether a lump of that Maſſie poiſon, ſo that if God ſhould<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> loke ſtrayghtly vpon him, his holineſſe ſhould not be able to abyde the tryall of the Lord. Finally the wiſedome of the fleſhe is death, and is at ſet battle in enimytie wyth God, for it is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Spirite nor the Law of God, neyther in deede<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ro. 8.7.8.</note> can be. So that I conclude with <hi>Paule,</hi> that they which be in the fleſh (and that is euery Popiſhe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiarie) cannot pleaſe God. Wherfore ſince the founteine of mans harte is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and poyſoned, what pleaſant action can proceede from his conduites? But ye will ſay, the regenerate man, meriteth. Yet <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth to the man regenerate, what haſt thou that thou haſt not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? I ſuppoſe <hi>Paule</hi> was regenerate, when he wrot his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes</hi> and yet he of himſelfe ſayth that his hart is combred wyth the Canker of ſinne. So that he dare not boaſt of meritte, but rather cryeth out, for woe agaynſt that guylt of his Regenerate fleſhe, ſaying.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 7.23.</note> I ſée another Lawe in my members rebelling agaynſt the Lawe of my mind,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:226:58"/> and leading me Captiue into the Lawe of Sinne, that is in my members. Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me from the bodye of this death, I thanke God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. His deſert here he confeſſeth to be ſuche, that were it not God through Chriſt our Lorde, he caried nothing with him, but a body (he meaneth ſoule and body) deſeruing by meritte euerlaſting death. And of his impoſſibilitie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme the act of Iuſtification by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, he in that place, a little before, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth ſaying,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro, 7.18.</note> for I know that in me, that is in my fleſhe, dwelleth no good thing, for to will is preſent wyth me, but I finde not meanes to perfourme that which is good, for I doe not that good thing that I would, but the euill that I would not, that doe I. If in the beſt ſort of men and moſt perfect, Sinne hath ſuch power, how ſhall the Papiſtes the ofſcourings of the Church boaſt of their worthinees? Nay neyther we, or our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are able to fulfyll<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 15.10.</note> the law, and therefore God<note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 8.3.</note> ſent his ſonne in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of ſinful fleſh, and for ſinne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb facs="tcp:226:59"/> ſinne in the fleſh, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the lawe ſhould be fulfilled in vs (that is to ſay by chriſt imputed to vs) which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit. And that no man ſhould boſt of his workes being regenerate, he more telleth vs, that God the father, which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ro. 8.11.</note> vp his ſon chriſt from death, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo quicken our mortal bodies, (not for any worthines in vs, but becauſe of his owne gift) eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bicauſe his ſpirit dwelleth in vs. Thus his diuine wiſdome hath diſpoſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, that both the action &amp; the cauſe of our true righteouſneſſe, may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcende one ſteppe from the maieſty of his throne of grace. Aſſure thy ſelfe therefore (Chriſtian reader) that in man is no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritte, vnleſſe to death for Sinne, which maketh al men<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ro. 3.19.</note> culpable before god: So it is his goodneſſe to haue mercy vpon all. Therfore if thou wilt atteyne to true righteouſneſſe, it is by the lawe, not of works<note n="e" place="margin">Ro. 3.22.</note> but of fayth in Ieſus Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to all, and vpon all that beleue. For the redemption is not in man regenerate or carnall, but in<note n="(f)" place="margin">Verſ. 24.</note> chriſt, who hath reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs to the father in his bloud, &amp; decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:226:59"/> our righteouſneſſe to come<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 3.26.</note> by the forgiuenes of our ſinnes, ſo preaching co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion &amp; ſhame to vs, &amp; the glory to him ſelfe. And albeit, that fayth which ſaueth, is called<note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 10.9.10 Io. 6.29.</note> a worke, yet is not the worke comming from the poure of man, for it is the worke of God, and his<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ro. 6. Phil. 36.</note> onely gift by the which we obteine chriſt, in whom we haue plentifull redemption from all our ſins. Now let vs ſpeak of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond branch, that is of mans impoſſibility to ſtand al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes fulfilling the law. The Scripture ſaith<note n="(d)" place="margin">Deut. 17.26 Gal. 3.10.</note> curſed is euery man that continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth not in al things which are written in the law, to doe them. And againe, when a<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eze. 18.</note> righteous man tourneth away from his righteouſnes and committeth iniury, he ſhal euen die, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. If once depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture from well doing, demerit death, and the iuſt<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pro. 24.26.</note> falleth ſeauen times, and ſince there is no fleſh that ſinneth not, nor any be he neuer ſo pefect, that alwaies conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth in well doing, I aſke, where ſhall we finde the meriting man? or who ſhall dare to preſent him before the Lorde, the reuenger of ſin? Or yet what is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can deliuer himſelfe from the danger of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:226:60"/> Curſe, due to his tranſgreſſions? Vaine therefore, and diueliſh is the confidence in ſuch Popiſh doctrine, and pernicious is the euill which this opinion bringeth to the ſoule, and great is the iniurie by it committed againſt chriſt Ieſus, the price of thy forgiuenes. The man meritor thru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteth Chriſt Crucifyed vnder his féet, &amp; ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth himſelfe vp in his ſtead, for his owne ſauiour, by his workes. But caſt thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt by ſcripturs audite &amp; at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foot of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thou ſhalt find this debt apparant to ſuch waſtfull ſpenders of their Lordes treaſure,<note n="a" place="margin">Ro. 9.30.</note> that ſuch as haue ſought righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of the law haue loſt the ſame, &amp; this remaineth recorded for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt, that all which ſought it by faith &amp; not by works<note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 9.30.31 32.</note> haue atteined to true righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes in déede. What then doth it profit good men to worke good works. The good wors of holy men profite <hi>2.</hi> waies. Firſt weighing their valoure wyth our dutie, they caſt downe our Peacoks tayle, and Egles hearte: béeing ſo farre ſhorte, of that they ſhould, they call mans crye, to vouche his ſtate vnprofytable<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk. 17.10. Mat. 25.30. Ro. 3.12.</note> to his Lorde. And ſo wyth crauinge Pardon for his ſinnes, fogetting his fewe déedes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:226:60"/> now<note n="(d)" place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> paſt, he haſteneth wyth humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the degrées of encreaſe,<note n="e" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.1</note> to walke and pleaſe God as he ought towards the throne of grace, where he ſéeth by fayth, himſelfe drawne vp wyth courage to reſt in Chriſt for lyfe, ſince his ſpirite liueth in him. Secondly they worke a moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red corroboration, in our hartes, whyleſt we conſider, of whom we haue ſuche grace. Euen that our hartes of <hi>Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant,</hi> are changed to fleſhye (not fleſhly) harts, &amp; into the ſame<note n="a" place="margin">Eze. 36.26.27.</note> Gods holy ſpirit is put (&amp; powred) by the power of which we are cauſe to walke in his lawes, and kepe his ſtatutes. Al which though we do not, or can, in ſuch ſort as we ſhould, yet becauſe his holy finger hath written his ſacred lawe<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iere. 31.33.</note> in our hartes, and put the ſinne into our inward parts, &amp; is himſelfe become by his couenant in chriſt, our god, and hath choſen vs for his holy people, for this cauſe I ſay he accepteth vs as iuſt, though we be all ſinners, and our works are acceptable in his ſight, and are not wythout their rewarde, yet of his mercye deuoyd of our merit, &amp; thus through our infirmitie worketh he his owne praiſe. So ende we the firſte parte of this verſe.
<pb facs="tcp:226:61"/> 
               <hi>To giue knowledge. &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond pointe is, to note whoſe ſinnes are forgiuen, and ſo conſequenly what kinde of perſons at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine truely and in déede to this ſaluation by his Prophets preached, and this I note of this word, <hi>To his people.</hi> For albeit that Chriſt is of the father giuen to the whole world, to be vnto them their ſauiour, and that there is no age or people vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the death of chriſt is not ſufficient to their ſaluation, and is therfore by himſelfe and the worde vouched the ſauiour<note n="(a)" place="margin">Luk. 2. Io. 3. Eph. 5. 1. Io. 4.14.</note> of the world, yet are not al people by him ſaued, nor any but ſuche as here be called his people. Now haue we alſo to conſider, that neither all that call, or chalenge to be his, are ſo in déede. For then ſhould not the Infidell &amp; Saracene with the Turke onely be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, becauſe they refuſe life,<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 33. 1. Io. 5.20.</note> which is only in chriſt Ieſus to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but alſo of that nomber which profeſſe chriſt in ſhew, and receiue the badge and ſeale of righteouſneſſe in Baptiſme, and in the dayes of their fleſh inuocate chriſt as God, and call the Father Lorde, be furthermore accompted to be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, and People of God, of this multitude
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:226:61"/> ſhall infinite walke the wandring path to eternall payne.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 7.21</note> 
               <hi>Not euery one that cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of God. &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are for a time in, but at no time are they of the church of God. Theſe eyther haue Satan to<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> pull the ſéede out of their hartes, leaſt they ſhould beleue and be ſaued, or beleue with ioye for a ſeaſon, and in fierie triall, vade and conſume to duſt and aſhes, and turne to their erſt conceiued death. But ſaluation ſtandeth at the<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> end of the race, happie is he that endureth to the end, for he ſhall be ſafe. Or els do they with the fayth in Chriſt, and goſpel of the ſonne of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedle the cares of this world, &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, which do choke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> growth of the ſéede, that no Wheate can come to ripenes for the Lordes barne, they begin in the ſpirite, but they<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 3.3</note> end in the fleſh. Theſe albeit they are bidden gheſtes, yet ſhall they not<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luc. 14.24. Mat. 22.7</note> once taſt of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromes ſupper. For they being called day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and the Lord with open armes euer readie to embrace them, refuſe to come<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pro. 1.26.27</note> therefore ſhall deſolation deuoure them, neither ſhall <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſaue them,
<pb facs="tcp:226:62"/> or the Sinagoge of Sathan, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> deliuer them from the wéeping ſtate and wofull paynes prepared for all hypocrites. Where in ſtéed of popiſh pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and carnall delights, ſhalbe mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and howling in perpetual chaines, nayled faſt to damnation his gaol. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe they neither heard or ſought the Lord, with integritie of ſoule, or worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him els, then with their owne inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hauing their harts a long eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from his delite. And albeit they were nouriſhed vp in the boſome of his beloued ſpouſe,<note place="margin">Papiſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Mice.</note> yet they are to him as Mice in the houſholders barne, whoſe purpoſe is to féede them fat, and fill their young of the corne, but not at any time to haue the preſence of the Maſters face. For whom alſo the huſband prepareth engins &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers them to conſume, though for a time he permit them to their deuiſed plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures. Such ſhalbe the end of al Papiſts, carnall proteſtants, &amp; fained hypocrites, which ſéeke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues altogether, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord at all. As daily thoſe perſons paſſe their time in ſuch wicked luſtes. But of farre other nature are the true people of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:226:62"/> God. As the other in the day of trial, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be knowne of him, for he ſhall ſay<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, I know ye not ye workers of iniquitie, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords people are knowne to him by their name, they are borne<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 3.5</note> againe of the ſpirit. They are<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.2</note> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied by the holy Ghoſt. They are graffed<note n="(d)" place="margin">Io. 15.1.2.3. Ro. 8.1</note> into Chriſt their vine. They are<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ephe 1.2.3.</note> predeſtinate to life. Choſen to bee the (f) ſonnes of God. Called to the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 8.30</note> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the word of ſaluation, and taught of God. The ſpirit of the ſonne is, by the loue of the moſt louing father, powred<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 4</note> into their harts, which cauſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to crie to him <hi>Abba</hi> father. Their ſtonie hartes hée mollifieth and turneth into hartes of fleſh, and into them for their direction and life he<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ezec. 36.25.26.27.28</note> putteth his ſpirit, by whoſe power through the woord ſowne and taught, he teacheth them his Lawes, and geueth them grace to walke in his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. Thus wrought by GOD, they bring forth holy fruites. They onely heare<note n="(d)" place="margin">Io. 10.3.4.5.</note> his voyce. All ſtraunge ſound, and charminge incantation, they vtterly auoyd, charme they (c) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo wiſely. They hunger after the
<pb facs="tcp:226:63"/> truth, and<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 119</note> thirſt the Lordes righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. They claſpe their harts by fayth in Chriſt, that through him alone they may apprehend the louing countenance of the heauenly Fathers face. They lay their<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 53.</note> ſinnes vppon his croſſe, and craue by comfortable cries in earneſt and ardent prayer, to be<note n="(g)" place="margin">1. Cor. 1 Ro. 5.21</note> clothed with his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. They euer confeſſe their many ſinnes, and aſſure them ſelues by fayth, of his ſaluation. They driue away<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 5.1.2.3.</note> terror, and reſt in the harbour of a quiet conſcience, and in moſt humble wiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche his throne of grace, as<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4.5 Ro. 8.15</note> deare children adopted in Chriſt, to their beſt beloued father. They loue to labour in godly workes, as by his word they are commaunded. They ſéeke to liue by faith<note n="c" place="margin">Abac. 2.4 2. Cor. 1.24</note> in Chriſt, as by the Scriptures they are taught. They ioy to ſuffer and beare his croſſe, and aſpiring by lowlineſſe of mind, they pray his aide and helpe there in, with comfort<note n="d" place="margin">2. cor. 1.4.5</note> continuing vnder the ſame. They appoynt no time for their<note n="(e)" place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> releaſe, but paciently abide his lotted ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. They looke not on the preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but weigh their ſinnes &amp; his decréed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:226:63"/> purpoſe and place, as oppoſite to their aſpect, the ioye that is<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb. 12.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.</note> ſet before them. They runne with patience the race for them appointed, and deſpiſing the preſent ſhame, they ſtill endure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, alwayes looking to Ieſus chriſt the authour &amp; fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of their life. They<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 5.44.45.</note> bleſſe thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> curſe them, they loue their enemies, and do good to<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 12.17.20.21.</note> all, but their chiefe delight is to ioyne with the houſhold of faith. They challenge to themſelues by nature confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſinne, and ſhame for their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and to God the father in Chriſt our Lord, by the inſtinct of his holy ſpirit, they attribute all honour and glory, and forgetting their workes paſt,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 3.13.14.15.</note> aſſay to go forwards to the price ſet before them, expreſſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by their good workes to be the Lords building, who hath made them an holy habitation, and a royall prieſthode. In hym they offer vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for a ſpirituall ſacrifice, dayly yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth the fruites of holy<note n="d" place="margin">Hoſe. 14.3 Heb. 13.15</note> lippes to his prieſt, and willing obedience to his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly will. They by the ſpirite deſire not to followe, but defie and kill the luſtes of the fleſh. They fight againſt Sathan, and his impes continually. They beare an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained
<pb facs="tcp:226:64"/>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.2 Gal. 4.9</note> hate to alſuperſtitious vanities. They contemne and deſpiſe the beggerly ordinances<note n="(f)" place="margin">Gal. 4</note> of the wicked world, diſday<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning to become bondſlaues to ſinne any more. They reioyce in their deliuerance, &amp; walke in the way of the lord with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere hart &amp; ſingle mind. Though ſlide they may eftſones by frayltie, yet neuer flatte fall they by falſhode, from the Lord their God. Lo theſe are they of whom our Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie ſpeaketh, and the Angell poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Joſeph</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 1</note> vnto, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he affirmeth Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to ſaue his people from their ſinnes. And all if theſe haue ſo many fraylties, &amp; be of ſuch weaknes, that they cannot as they would, or do as they ſhould, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walke before the Lord: Yet ſhall they not feare, for his Chriſt is theirs, &amp; with him they haue<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 1</note> in him iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, redemption, and perfect wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. By whoſe vertues and merites they are euer preſented before God, as a iuſt and holy people peculiar to the Lord. To theſe can come<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ro. 8.1</note> no condemnation, or any accuſation ſhalbe admitted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor any gilt procure ſentence to their loſſe. For it is the Lord that doth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:226:64"/> iuſtifie them. Finally no power ſhall or can conuenting, conuince them. For they haue in their hartes the word, which is<note n="d" place="margin">Ro. 1</note> Gods power to ſaluation. And God him ſelfe ſtandeth on their ſide for their defence. So that it is more poſſible for light to become darknes, good euill, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill good, which neuer ſhall come to paſſe: then that the Lordes people ſhould not be deliuered from death, or yet want the knowledge of their ſaluation. Which knowledge teacheth them to féele in hart and find by truth, that the ſame ſauing health conſiſteth not in their remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but commeth of god: (for his Chriſts ſake) by full remiſſion of and from all their ſinnes. The Lord graunt vs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſo in his vineyarde, which profeſſe his name, that we may be (not called on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) but appeare in déede his choſen people. Then ſhall we be ſure of our deliuerance in Chriſt our Sauiour. And thus much for theſe wordes <hi>his people,</hi> in this preſent verſe mentioned.</p>
            <p>The third &amp; laſt branch of this verſe is, to conſider by what meanes his people are brought to féel &amp; perceiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:226:65"/> doth conſiſt in the remiſſion geuen of god Namely by this, that the ſame is made knowne to their conſciences, by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the word preached vnto them. For all if, the price of Chriſtes bloud, bée they moſt ſoueraigne ſalue for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſinne, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it is wholy waſhed away: Yet onleſſe the Church of God haue ſence, and perfect féeling hereof in her inward partes and depeneſſe of hart, the ſame ſhall nothing profite her. For the which cauſe Chriſt promiſeth being once lift vp<note n="a" place="margin">Io. 3.14.15.</note> as the ſerpent in the wilderneſſe was, to draw all men to looke and come to him by the inſtrument of fayth, and to his hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly father, in that his moſt comfortable prayer a little before his death, for the comfort of his elect, he witneſſeth that life eternall conſiſteth in the knowledge of God the father and Chriſt his Sonne. Alſo reprouing the Iewes for their rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, he chargeth their<note n="b" place="margin">Io. 8.37.55.</note> ignorance to bée the cauſe therof, as alſo ſhewing his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of their perſecuted ſtate &amp; perils to death, affirmeth<note n="(c)" place="margin">Io. 16.2.3.</note> ignorance to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing meane hereto. <hi>This ſhal they do ſaith he, becauſe they neither know the father nor
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:226:65"/> yet me. Paule</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle teſtifieth this to be the meane to apprehend ſaluation, euen to come to the knowledge of the truth. Thereto he ioyneth it to the branch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, ſaying<note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4</note> 
               <hi>God will haue all men to be ſaued, and to come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> Lo: a thing moſt incident to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is to haue knowledge of the truth. To conclude, who are they which are taught of god, but his people? And what are they taught of him, but the truth of his word? Which he writeth with his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in their hartes, as the ſcripture ſaith, that they may be a knowing people, and not ignorant as the Papiſtes teach, but falſely, the ſame to be the mother of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But Chriſt ſayth, that ignorance is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 8.19</note> the mother of error, which leadeth to damnation. Behold now, the ſcope of this Baptiſts office was to prepare the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh harts, by the knowledge of their ſinnes and repentance for the ſame to preuent Gods Iuſtice, by fruitefull acceptation of the Goſpell by Chriſt preſently preached, to haue him for there God, and by him ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation and full deliuerance from their ſinnes. For the which cauſe the Angell
<pb facs="tcp:226:66"/> alſo before to Zacharie<note n="(b)" place="margin">Lu. 1.15.16.17.</note> adorned him with noble titles, and not to him only doe they belong, but to all the true preachers of God with him, wherefore they are here of thée (deare Reader) the better to bée weighed, as wordes that doe import the glory of his heauenly Embaſſage, to thine earthly hart. Hée is firſt ſayd to bée full of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Titles giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God to Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</note> a thing moſt neceſſarie to bée in the true preacher of the word, as without the ſame he can neither preach, much leſſe profite the people of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles from chriſt therfore recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the fulnes of his ſpirit by portion to their aptnes, &amp; power to<note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. 2.3.4.</note> execute their office, &amp; he breathed<note n="d" place="margin">Iohn. 20.22</note> on them, and gaue them his holy ſpirite, that thereby they might not only abound in gifts, but alſo ſhould without terror ſpeake his wil, and preach his name to all nations. So in like maner <hi>Paule</hi> witneſſeth that both the gift of prophecying, &amp; Prophets,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ephe. 4.11. 1. Cor. 12.11 27.28.</note> Doctors and teachers, is by the ſpirite of God. Of which grace he hath promiſed continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the end of the world, ſaying: <hi>J</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Math. 28.20</note> 
               <hi>wil be with you to the end of the world.</hi> And therfore <hi>Iohn</hi> warneth thée (reader) not to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:226:66"/> beleue euery<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Io. 4.2</note> ſpirite (ſo he calleth the doctrine by the preacher brought) but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth thée to trie whether they be of God. He ſheweth thee abſolutely that in the preachers of thy age, Gods ſpirit alſo ſpeaketh, ſaying: <hi>Hereby ſhall ye knowe the Spirite of GOD. Euerye ſpirite that confeſſeth that Jeſus Christe is come in the Fleſhe, is of GOD.</hi> There were falſe Prophets among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> which kept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people backe from the faith in Chriſt. There were certaine heritiques which denied Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures teach him. And theſe ſo vexed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, and moleſted the conſciences of the godly bretherne, and began to make ſuch ſhipwracke of the faith of many, that the Apoſtle was driuen (from the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to frame their hartes in Chriſt,) to arme by inſtruction the church of GOD, againſt <hi>Cerinthus Ebyon</hi> and other heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, that woulde not acknowledge Chriſt wholy as the Scriptures proued him to bée. The like proofe of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is left to thée, to the ends of the world, to trie the Preachers which come vnto thée, whether they haue in them, or doe by Gods ſpirite ſpeake vnto thée.
<pb facs="tcp:226:67"/> He that preacheth Ieſus Chriſt as hée is ſet downe in the written Scriptures, is of God. Hée that denieth him in any part their vouched to be in Chriſt, is of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Whoſoeuer hath not this<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Io. 4.3.</note> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and is a preacher, cannot but by the ſpirite of Sathan vtter as by his receiued ſpirite, all lying fables, as<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Re. 22.23.24</note> 
               <hi>Zedkia</hi> the falſe prophet did to <hi>Achab.</hi> And both <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> manifeſtly ſhew vnto vs, that many ſuch falſe Prophets ſhall riſe vp in the laſt dayes, which ſhal alſo denie chriſt in déede, albeit they confeſſe him with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked words. <hi>Paule</hi> giueth thée notes infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, that euer ſhall lead thée to a right iudgement of theſe ſpirits of error, &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of diuels.<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1.2.3.4.</note> Firſt they ſhall ſpeake lies by hypocriſie fayning truth, but trie them by the rule giuen of chriſt, <hi>ſearch the ſcriptures,</hi> which order the Citizens of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 17.11</note> are ſaid to obſerue when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught them. <hi>2.</hi> They ſhal forbid to marrie, and who doth forbid I pray thée (take vew) that miniſters may not Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>not the ſcripture,</hi> but rather the flat<note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2 Tit. 1.6.1.102.9.1.2.</note> contrarie? Who doth forbid that holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god in Paradiſe to auoyd ſinne,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:226:67"/> but the Pope y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter of ſinne? he doth forbid it <hi>to all his ſacrificing prieſtes,</hi> at all times, yet whoredome he permitteth to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder purchaſed warrant to al time, To al other chriſtians he forbiddeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage at certaine times, as <hi>Aduent, Lent, Jmber daies. &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Siricius</hi> one of the Popes, condemneth mariage to be a fruit of the fleſh, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſtate a man can not pleaſe god. Meats which god hath crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to be receiued with thanks geuing, &amp; is made<note n="f" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.5.</note> holy by his word &amp; praier, doth this beaſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dragon<note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 1..11.12.</note> 
               <hi>Satanas</hi> in paine of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, forbid to al at his appoynted times. And the breakers of his lawe, (though bleſſed of God) are of him curſed with booke, bell and candle, out of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen (as <hi>Paſquine</hi> calleth it) earth, and this naturall life, as Lollords &amp; heriticks not worthy the benefite of temporall quiet. Theſe ſaith <hi>Paule</hi> in the place before quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are the doctrines of Diuels.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Behold the popiſh doctrine from whence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and of what ſpirite it is. Flie from it, as from hel it ſelfe. <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note place="margin">.2 Pet. 2.4</note> warning our times of the like falſe ſpirite ſayth, But there were falſe Prophets alſo among
<pb facs="tcp:226:68"/> the people, euen as there ſhalbe falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers among you, which priuely ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denying the Lord that hath bought them, &amp; bring vpon them ſelues, ſwift damnation. And many ſhall followe their damnable wayes, by whom the way of truth ſhalbe euill ſpoken of: And through couetouſnes ſhall they with fayned words make mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of you, whoſe iudgement long agone is not farre of, and their damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſléepeth not. Lay this Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy hart, and indifferently meaſure thereby the Popiſh Church and doctrine, and thou ſhalt ſée (as it were) the Apoſtle to paynt the ſinfull Sinagoge of <hi>Rome</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thy proſpect. With what humblenes of Angels créepe they craftely into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of men? what opinions bréed they flat condemned by the word? How open they their mouthes to ſlaunder the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of our Chriſt? and cal it hereſie, though not as it lieth in leaues, but as it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached by gods holy prophets in this our dayes? And what loue they haue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word it ſelfe (do thou iudge) when hauing the gouernment, they burned the Bibles, raſed the ſcriptures from of the walles in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:226:68"/> churches &amp; els, &amp; to that they could burned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> letters in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacred fleſh of chriſtes martirs. What marchaundiſe of mens ſoules is there in poperie? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their God, their pope, their reliques &amp; ſaints merits, their <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> their heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; helly pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatorie, thier Maſſes &amp; pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, their whole power &amp; pelf is ſet at price, &amp; al for monei? What ſinne in man ſo horrible, that ſhuld not there haue pardon for money? What wicked fact pretended, ſhall not there for money not only be pardoned, but warran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted? Amongſt the ſinnes againſt the <hi>2.</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, is there a greater then Treaſon? I ſay treaſon to god his religion, his prince and vicar, by his great mercy ſet ouer vs in this natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? And is not the Pope y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head practiſer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? Doth not he looſe that in earth by his Bul, which god hath moſt ſurely tied faſt in heauen by his word? the ſworne and natural due obedience to her Maieſtie? Doth not he promiſe abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where God pronounceth curſe and damnation?<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> To whatſoeuer perſon which reſiſteth his power? And is this for any other cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bring your purſes to his coffers, &amp; your ſoules to ſwift dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? Looke vpon the <hi>Gnat,</hi> by that moſt
<pb facs="tcp:226:69"/> precious <hi>Iewell,</hi> the reuerend Biſhop late of <hi>Sarum,</hi> brought forth to the vew of all mens ſight, in his learned<note n="(b)" place="margin">Def. Apol fol. 793</note> anſwere to halting <hi>Harding,</hi> and thou ſhalt not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile though he wold haue vs his again, that <hi>Camels</hi> in great number (and yet ſcarſely could) might yearely conuey his huge ſommes of money out of this nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Reioyce O England for thy deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, embrace the word by Gods ſpirite put in the mouthes of thy learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and others their godly brethern, in moſt pleniiful wiſe: So ſhal thy hart yéeld faithful loue &amp; true obedience to our godly Quéen, &amp; thou ſhalt reape her aid for thy quiet, but chiefely Gods bleſſing for thy ſoules health in his Chriſt, againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of error and Sathan himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly to him vz. to his office &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is aſcribed a certaine power to turne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers to their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This power is by his preaching the word, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of god directing him: where note that the word preached, is of power to<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 19.7</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, bicauſe it is the (b) mallet of God to beat downe ſinne, and his two edged<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 6.17</note> ſword, to cut downe vice. The<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2</note> mylke of GOD, to nouriſh and alter the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:226:69"/> crooked nature, of mans corpupted fleſhe. The ſéede to<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 13. 1. Pet. 1.23.</note> make him a fruitfull ground, the pleaſaunt<note n="(f)" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.15. Pſal. 119.</note> Odor, to delight that faythfull ſcent. The faythfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the poure<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ro. 1.</note> of God, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Satan and his aſſaultes. To beate downe ſtrong holdes, and euery<note n="(h)" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.</note> height that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and to bring and leade cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to the obedience of Chriſte, euery thought: and full power the worde hath to be reuenged of all the obſtinate, when the obedience of the faythfull is fulfilled. It is not for other cauſe that God doth ſpare the wicked, then that the Godly ſhould firſt be brought to more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the wicked ſhould waxe more rype in their iniquitie, and that the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by their tyranie, might dayly<note n="(i)" place="margin">Iud. 2.22.23</note> be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and that for a ſeaſon they deuoure the noyſome creatures<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ex. 23.28.29</note> of the earth, that elſe would more hurte the children of God. But when the Aples<note n="(b)" place="margin">Amos. 8 Iere. 24.9.</note> be rype, the Lorde will pull the trée, and caſt the fruite into the fyre. For the wicked as he cannot forget, ſo wil he in his appoynted time, poure out the dregges of his angry
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:226:70"/> muſt be taken away and remoued. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry valley muſt be exalted, euery moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine brought low, the croked muſt be ſtreyght framed, and the rough wayes made playne, and this preparation muſt be by the preaching of the Goſpell: ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth <hi>Luke</hi> the place, or rather the Angel when he ſaith to <hi>Zachary,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>J. Bap.</hi> ſhould make ready a people inſtructed for the Lorde. As <hi>Jhon</hi> behaued him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, ſo dyd the Apoſtles faythfully, and the Fathers of olde ſincerely in this their charge, Remaineth that the Princes and Preachers now be diligent therein, as beſt beſéemeth their vocation, to prepare his holy wayes.</p>
            <p>The way of the Lord is in mans hart, which agaynſt the comming of his God,<note place="margin">How the Lords way muſt bee prepared.</note> the king of al kinges, he muſt ſo prepare, that there be nothing to offend his eye, or hinder his louing comming. If an earthly Prince ſhal come to a Towne or Citye, how are the wayes ſkoured, the path made playne, the ſtreates ſo ſanded, that the very Horſe ſhall not haue wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to trip. The houſe paynted, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duites running wyne, the place perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:226:70"/> and ſo garniſhed, that his delight may féede wyth pleaſure vpon the view of this prepared way. This would the Baptiſt haue vs to thinke vpon, when he alludeth to the comfortable comming of their mightie kings, and the pompous preparations of the people for his receipt. But ſith Chriſtes comming is into the ſoule of man by his Spirite, the path of mans conſcience muſt be prepared in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſort, aſwel in matters of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer wicked life, for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in chriſt Ieſu<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.17.</note> vnles he be made a new creature. The path of our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ought to he fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, neyther ought we, or may we,<note place="margin">Deut. 12.32</note> wythout mere ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crileadge, adde thereto, or diminiſhe, in the worſhippe of the mightie <hi>loue,</hi> in Chriſt, eny thing at all. Thriſe Curſed be the Papiſtes therefore, that leape vp into Chriſtes Throane, and thruſt him to the walles, ſetting vp a will worſhip<note n="b" place="margin">Col 2.18.19.22.23.</note> of their owne inuention, hauing no other warrant then the fleſhe that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that Idolatrie. But the Scripture holde all them<note n="c" place="margin">Eſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11.20</note> accurſed that ſet vppe falſe worſhip vnto him, or that builde
<pb facs="tcp:226:71"/> their neſts in mans ſtrength,<note place="margin">Ro. 23.24.1.25.26. &amp;c.</note> or put their truſt in fleſhly wiſdome, or turn the glory of God to a mortall man, or ſet their affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce in their inuentions.</p>
            <p>O ye mightie mageſtrates, in and of the church of chriſt, to you this chiefly doth be long, ſo to prepare this heauenly path, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no offenſiue matter be there left to ſtay or ſtop his godly preſence from our harts. You are to<note n="d" place="margin">2. Re. 22.</note> enter the path appoynted to the lord his vſe, &amp; to remoue out of the way, euery baſe &amp; beggerly matter that is to the diſhonor of God, ſet vp as to his worſhip, or garniſhing falſly of his houſe, the rudiments of men, which can neuer edifie in the Church of God. And to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund &amp; ſend abroad the Preachers and forerunners of this king, to cry for prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to euery rugged hart, &amp; depreſſed conſcience, with the weight of ſin, that by the comfort of chriſts goſpel, they may be brought to lift vp the eies of their faith, to the lord in <hi>Sion.</hi> There Ieſus chriſt is ſet vp for their ſaluation, there ſhall their heauie harts &amp; laden ſoules, haue<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> new refreſhing in him, the Lord crucified, &amp; of his Father againe rayſed to lyfe<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:226:71"/> their iuſtification. And you Baptiſts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, your dutie is to pull out of mens hartes, by ſound &amp; moderate doctrine, the God<note n="(c)" place="margin">Dan. 11.30 39.</note> 
               <hi>Maiſim,</hi> and euery height that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth it ſelfe<note n="(d)" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.</note> againſt God. The pryd of mans hearte, by the power of the worde, muſt you beate downe, which proudly ſay wyth Popiſh ſpyte. <hi>Sic volumus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The popiſh ſpeach of Engliſhe papiſtes.</note> ſo we will haue it, and not by the word to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the time &amp; cauſe, whether ſo it ought to be. All ſuch as ſet vp their hornes on high againſt Chriſtes lowly members, and nothing lyke of, that the path might ſomthing be ſkowred: ſuch be they which fight for lyfe with tooth and nayle (as the prouerbe is) to kéepe vppe the troublous thickets, and the loftie hye hilles that can not ſtoupe to the Lordes lawe. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, <hi>Atheistes,</hi> and Hypocrites, of our dayes I meane, which all though they be woll ſhrubbed, and ſhred, yet they begin euen nowe before the ſpringe, to budde, and hope againe in time to floriſh as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gréen bay trée.<note place="margin">Pſal. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But were they lopped dazie height, or proined y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyth princely <hi>Dauids</hi> a cutting knife, they as the ſhred willow, floriſh in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but neuer eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones
<pb facs="tcp:226:72"/> could they take roote. The ragged hartes, which wyth the Hare ſkipe here and there, to flye from trueth, whoſe ſmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed lippes imbrace diſſimulation, your ſeaſoned ſound w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Helias</hi> hart (oh ye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the Lorde) muſt ring wyth pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into their eares. For moſt abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is the halting Hypocrite, he is a<note n="(b)" place="margin">Micah. 7.4</note> Thornie Hedge and Buſhe of Briers, to wounde and ſtinge as many as be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his companie. The harte<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.1.</note> chaffed wyth flyght, ſéeketh to the Riuers of water for his comfort. But the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryte purſued by Satan to his deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath no luſt to looke after the water of<note n="(d)" place="margin">Io. 7.38.39.</note> lyfe, which God doth giue to all that fathfully thirſt therefore. Oh let them know that wholy, chiefely, and for lyfe, they ought to ſéeke the ſame, in ſinceritie of harte, wythout Hypocriſie. Thus my deare Bretherne we ought in my Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to teache the Lordes flocke,<note place="margin">Diuiſion in the church perilous.</note> to kill Satan, and beate downe ſinne, and not wyth bitterneſſe of penne, and carping ſpeache in Pulpits, through byting one an other, to bring that promiſe (or iuſte threat) vpon vs, you ſhall be<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 5.15.</note> deuoured
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:226:72"/> one of another.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 5.15.</note> The LORDE amend this euill, and graunt vs more<note n="(b)" place="margin">Cal. in 1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſ. ad Cor. cap. 11. verſ. 16. conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſum. &amp;c.</note> carefull ouer his Heritage for his names ſake. Whereſoeuer the Preacher findeth the people voide of theſe effectes, (as wher is not this ragged deſert?) There ought hee to prepare a path by the doctrine of the worde, which is of power to conuerte the loſte childe of Iſraell. To preach the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable cauſes in Chriſt to allure vs, and to ſhewe vs the horrible ſtate of our own corrupted nature, and the gréedie deſire that ſathan hath of our deſtruction. Can men thinke with doubleneſſe of harte to pleaſe the Lorde? Can they ſerue God by halfes? Or go towards him as far as the lawes of men leade or compell them and no further, and yet of God be well accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? If God be God<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Re. 18.21.</note> follow him, if <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> be he, go after him. If <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> (whoſe weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming many make to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues a ſiniſter refug) had not proceded to more perfection, hee had not aduentured to<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 7.65.</note> aunſwer in Chriſtes behalfe to the counſel, or yet<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 19.38.39</note> of ſo great a tiran as <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> was, durſt he haue begged the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 19.38.39</note> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Ieſus, or againſte the malice of ſo many cruell ennemies, haue ioyned with
<pb facs="tcp:226:73"/> noble <hi>Joſeph</hi> in ſo hard a ſute. The luke warme perſons, that be neyther hote nor colde, are as a burden and ſurffet to the Lordes ſtomack, which he hath promiſed to<note n="(c)" place="margin">Apoc. 3.16 Good coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell to hipo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crites.</note> vomit out of his mouth. Loue the Prince, and liue in and vnder her graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gouernement, ye Papiſts and <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtes,</hi> and Hipocrites alſo, for the Lordes ſake. Let his holy Lawe force you, as a moſte abſolute Iniunction, to her godly Lawes, and not (as you ſay pollitiquely, but popiſhly,) to leane to his law becauſe of her graces iniunctions. Neither halve before God, to refuſe your obedience to religion; Gods Sacraments, and deuine ſeruice in the Churche, nowe godly ſet downe: vſing your clawing coolour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome and ſuche do not obſerue the ſaide Iniunctions.<note place="margin">The perfect Papiſt abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the law to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to creepe into fauour and eſcape trial.</note> For it is more then ſene to al, that a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of you make thoſe Iniunctions, (which at the firſte were ſet downe to bring you forwarde) a preſente let to your obedience, &amp; a cloke for your maliciouſneſſe. The actes and wordes of ſuch as moleſt the godly quiet, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red peace of the church, I wil not, or may defende. I lamente the cauſe, and praye
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:226:73"/> God to ceaſe the action, to his glory,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Marloratus in 1. Cor. ca 11 ver. 19. probatus.</note> the peace of his Church, and the extirpation of the ſerpent, and all his, at his good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time. But you diſſembling Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, are lyke vnto the wicked perſons in the dayes of <hi>Darius,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Da. 6.1.2.3.</note> who fearinge leaſte <hi>Daniel</hi> with his religion ſhould be preferred,<note place="margin">The papiſts pollicie to ſtoppe the paſſage of the worde.</note> ſought by all meanes to claſpe that holy Prophet vnder the Kinges In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, to his deſtruction. So it is not the loue ye haue to our godly Elizabeth, whom ye wiſh to giue place to your <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> but the Lord wil &amp; doth laughe your deuiſes to ſcorn, his name be praiſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and her graces good Lawes, but the hate which you haue conceaued againſte <hi>Daniel</hi> the <hi>(e)</hi> Prophetes of the Lord,<note place="margin">Act. 24.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8</note>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, they ſéeke to enſtruct you the right way, to make you prepared for the Lord) and to reclaime you from popery to the profeſſed trueth: many of you hauinge blinde eyes, voyde of ſight, by the reaſon of hardneſſe<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb 6.6. Eph. 4.18.19.</note> of your hartes the which cannot repent, pray ayd at the ſame law, which your ſelues moſt deadly hate. No doubt, concerning the miniſters and prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers (admitte they be good proteſtants) they be al of like accompt in your audite,
<pb facs="tcp:226:74"/> as well the trew and faithfull paſtours, which obſerue the appointed order, as ſuch other their godly Brethren,<note place="margin">Rites not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſed, for contempt of moderat miniſters.</note> which (wading no further) vnwilling were to vſe the ſame, not contemptuouſly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing becauſe of the precept, but moderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by petition (regardinge theyr peoples quiet or hurt) with humbleneſſe of harte pray God and craue, at the Gods <hi>(a)</hi> in earth (by his power placed ouer vs) as foloweth. Mercifully vouchſafe, O ye god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Princes of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> that as<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> may not refuſe circumciſion, where <hi>Paule</hi> ſéeth the infirmities of the Iewes to require the ſame, and the Chuche her néede of ſuch a teacher: So let not<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 2.3.4</note> 
               <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> be compelled thervnto, where as falſe Brethren priuily créepe in, to bring into bondage the children of the lord. No place wold <hi>Paule</hi> admit to ſuch, though elſwher he<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 21.21.10. &amp; ve. 27</note> conſideringe the weakeneſſe of the Iewes, refuſed not to aſociate the <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with the ſhauing of hys head, according<note n="(e)" place="margin">Nom. 6.13</note> to the lawe, though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid the gentils, hee reproued <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Gal. 2.11</note> for the like Iewiſh obſeruation. And when it ſhal pleaſe thee (O Lord) graunt our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:226:74"/> Princes hart, further prepared to ſcoure the Lordes pathe, by godly aduiſe of her noble councellers, that by her pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authority, and not our priuate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes, all ſuch matter may bee remoued as worke no way the profit of his church. And to vs miniſters and men, her graces ſubiectes, prayer and trewe patient obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, regarding more the loue and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of the Churche, then our owne lyke or priuate<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.18.19.20.21.22.</note> deſiers. No leſſe praiſe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the good Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroying<note n="b" place="margin">Hiſ. tripar. li. 10. ca. 27.</note> the idolatrous temples, then godly<note n="(c)" place="margin">VVolphi. in 2. Re. ca. 23. Trip. hiſt. li. 6. ca. 1. fo. 412.</note> 
               <hi>Constantine,</hi> in ſhutting vp theyr gates. Faithfull <hi>Joſias,</hi> in his reformation thought it beſt to breaketh<note n="d" place="margin">2. Re. 23.12. &amp; 25. verſe.</note> Aulters, and caſt the duſte of them into the brooke <hi>Kedron,</hi> and the Scripture ſaith to his commendation, that before him there was no ſuch king that turned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, with all his harte and all his ſoule, and with all his might, according to the lawe of <hi>Moiſes,</hi> neither after him aroſe there any ſuch. This example ſaith one learned<note n="e" place="margin">VVolphius in .2. Re. ca. 23.</note> writer is written to teach vs, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe and vtterly deſtroy all Idolles, and euery entiſment of ſuperſtition, that
<pb facs="tcp:226:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:226:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:226:76"/> no parte of ſuch monumentes, be lefte t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> admoniſh the poſterity. <hi>Muſculus</hi> vpon the ſentence by God giuen to the ſerpent, (the inſtrument wherwith the Serpent deceyued <hi>Heua,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 3</note> and brought <hi>Adam</hi> to ſinne) aſketh a queſtion,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Muſculus in Gen. ca. 3.4.1.</note> whether the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence were iuſt, ſince the ſerpent was not the author, but the organ wherwith: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing priuie to Sathans purpoſe or wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing hurt, but was ſorced by Sathan therto? He alſo anſwereth, yea: not onely becauſe it procéeded from the iuſt God, but geuing reaſon for the ſame, ſaith: it is very right that to the greater deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſathans malice, fraud, and diſceit, not only himſelf, but all his inſtruments wherewith hee worketh his malice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſubiect and receiue like iudgement with him. For like as ſaith he euery ſuch inſtrument, wherewith any good thing or felicitie is brought to paſſe, deſerueth, and is worthely beloued and had in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: So by the ſame right, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of deſtruction, of what nature or condition ſo euer they bee, are together with the author of them to be punniſhed and condemned. Hereto he alleadgeth
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:226:76"/> certaine examples of ſcriptures, as of<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ioſ. 7 Nomb. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Achan,</hi> of <hi>Corah</hi> and his companie. In end he thus concludeth. If to condemne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> organ with the wicked ſpirit the author, it be <hi>Iniquum:</hi> So by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame reaſon muſt it be wicked, that the bodies of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, together with their ſoules be made partakers of eternall life and heauenly felicitie. But farre be ſuch thoughts from the minds of the godly, &amp;c. Thus farre <hi>Muſculus.</hi> That old father and great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctor <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> vppon the ſame place of Geneſis, geueth in effect the ſame cenſure, whoſe wordes vpon the <hi>Serpents</hi> iudgement are (as they are reported alſo by <hi>Peter Martir,</hi> that famous man) thus.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pet. Martit. in Gen. 3. c.</note> God in this action delt like vnto a man that is a moſt naturall louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who when he ſéeth his deare ſonne ſlaine, doth not only couet the death of the murtherer, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, Speare, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery the inſtrument wherewith he peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, will he likewiſe ſéeke to deſtroy. Should I ſtand to ſpeake of al lets &amp; rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh in this nation, I ſhould fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſelf to al fleſh, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out great ſearch, ſee ſuch matter abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as no reaſonable volume could co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine their deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Idolatrous papiſts
<pb facs="tcp:226:77"/> Atheiſtes, Carnalites, Hipocrites, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, Drunkardes, and ſundry wicked vices elſe, in many places, many times, are leſſe loked vpon with iuſtice cenſure, then ſuch as (many wayes els) are profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers in the church of god. This is a perilous ſhrub, it would be ſtubbed vp by the rootes. The Lord graunt better regard, leſt the maieſtie on hye take the matter into his owne hand, from ſuch as be ouer negligent<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 82.5.6.7.8.</note> Gods in earth. The Preachers, of God muſt cry out in Sion, and tell Ieruſalem and Iuda<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſa. 58.1.</note> of her faults, from the hieſt to the loweſt, to one and other, for &amp; agaynſt this &amp; that euill. In paine<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eze. 3.32.</note> of damnation muſt the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher cry out, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſert may be tracked, and the hils, the valleyes, the ragged, the croked, the old, and rotten for age, may be altered or quite remoued: that in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land his prophets may ſo<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ro. 15.16.</note> exhibit to the lord at his comming, a prepared people, and well inſtructed, whoſe ſoules by his ſpirit being<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 8.11.12.13.14.</note> gouerned, their bodies by his force ſhall walke in all holines, in his ſight as the dayes of their lyfe. Then will the Lord yet more delight in our Church,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:226:77"/> ſtate, and people, he will take pleaſure to walke into the garden of our harts, there to receiue the redolent ſmell of the ſwete fruites, ſpreading themſelues far abroad, all a long the beds of fayth, he will bleſſe her with beautie, and builde hir with pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious ſtones<note n="(f)" place="margin">Eſa. 54.</note> of great price, he wil teach this nation himſelfe by his worde, and will giue thée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more abounding ſpirit to walke in his ſtatutes, he wil be for thée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thy forren foes &amp; domeſticall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, a tower of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to aſſiſt thée, and bruſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in myerie ſtreates<note n="(a)" place="margin">Micah. 7.10</note> before thy eyes, he will deſtroy the ſmyth, and all<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſa. 54.16.17.</note> his inſtrumentes: the Pope and his pelfe, &amp; all diueliſhe deuiſes agaynſt thée, of what force ſo euer. To his faythfull miniſters and Teachers, will he graunt his<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iere. 1.18.</note> ayde and power, to be for them a well fenced cytie, wyth walles of Braſe, agaynſt all Popiſhe practiſes, bent to their deſtruction. Finally to ſome &amp; all, from thy vertuous Quéene, to the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Plowman ſowing his ſéede, will he poure forth his grace and ſpirit, his chriſt and heauen, to be thine for euer.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:226:78"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11.12.</label> Through the tender mercy of our God, whereby the day ſpring from an high, hath viſited vs. To giue light to them that ſit in darkeneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death, and to guide our feet into the way of peace.</q>
            <p>This knowledge of Saluation, where by man is brought to the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes in chriſt, commeth not to vs by purchaſe of gold and ſiluer, or any other mans merit, but by the inward mercy of our God (ſayth <hi>Zachary</hi>) euen as a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall mother ſéeing her child wounded in her armes, or taken violently from her to be ſlaine, all the partes of her body, and ſoule are therewith moued with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler compaſſion: ſo haſt thou O God (ſaith he) beholding our moſt miſerable blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; bandage vnder ſinne, taken moſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:226:78"/> mercifull pitie, &amp; in the bowels of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly mercies, haſt ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vs this branch, thy Chriſt, &amp; day ſpring, as the beautie<note n="(a)" place="margin">Col. 1.15 Heb. 1 3</note> of thy fleſh, to viſit our darkeneſſe with the light of his trueth, and by his lyfe to deliuer vs from the gloming darke death of ignorance &amp; ſinne, &amp; to ſet our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence quiet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuſtification by his bloud to embolden vs to approch thy preſence; as Children to their beſt beloued Father, without terror of death for Sinne, or feare of any worldly want. For through the comfort of this bright ſhining ſunne of righteouſneſſe and virident braunche of <hi>Jeſse</hi> his roote, the anoynted Chriſt, we ſhall ouercome whatſoeuer ſhall ſet it ſelfe againſt vs.</p>
            <p>To our inſtruction &amp; further comforts, let vs as before, ſo in theſe two verſes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ſome ſuch pith as lieth within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of theſe happy words. By this maner of ſpeach, the Prophet would haue vs to conſider déeply the chiefe and aboundant<note n="(b)" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3.</note> loue of the ineffable God, whoſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and care (as it were) is onely bent to doe vs the beſt good, though we in no part demerit the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:226:79"/>
            <p>Thrée ſpeciall, thinges I obſerue to thée (gentle reeder (in theſe laſt verſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt followeth.<note n="a" place="margin">Io. 3.16.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, that by the only mercy of God without the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of man, Chriſt our Sauiour is giuen to vs, as himſelfe teſtifieth, in the third of Iohn ſaying: So dearely God loued the world that hee gaue his onely begotten Sonne. &amp;c. Without our merit gaue the heauenly Father his ſauing Chriſt, for when we were<note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 5.8.9.10 11.</note> his ennemies he ſaued vs. Vpon the which moſt mercifull acte he perſwadeth vs, that now much more ſence we belong to him, will he deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrath. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond note is, that albeit God in his great mercy hath ſo copiouſly enritched vs with the hidden treaſure of ful remiſſion from al our ſinnes: yet hath he therwith nothing impared his iuſtice, but hath by the merit of another himſelfe Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, (which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet here calleth the day ſpring from an high) fully anſwered the ſame. In whoſe perſon mercy<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 101.1 Pſal. 85.9.10 11.12.13.</note> &amp; iuſtice, haue met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; mercy &amp; peace, haue kyſſed each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for in that Chriſt Ieſus, tooke vpon him our<note n="(d)" place="margin">He. 1.9.10 11.12.13.14.15.16.17.18.</note> nature, &amp; ſanctifiing the ſame
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:226:79"/> by his conception and ioined it to his god head. He tooke that perſon of ſinne vppon him, which could be ſubiecte to the croſſe, and aptly receiued the curſe due thereto for our iniquitie, and accept to the ful, the fury of his fathers iuſt conceiued wrath. In which body<note n="(e)" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24</note> he did fully beare the ſame vpon the croſſe in his bitter death, at what time the angrie countinance of his God, with the full paines of hell, for mans ſin was wholy laide vpon him: hee was compelled with vehemency to cry<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mar. 15.</note> my God my God, why haſte thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me?</p>
            <p>The fruite of this death is ſuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as no one of vs hath put our hand to this croſſe, with him to cary his Fathers wrath for our ſin: ſo hath he obtained ſuch redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as none of vs that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ro. 8.1 Io. 3 1. Iohn. 2.2. Math. 3.17.</note> beléeue a right in him, ſhal or can taſt any part of conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Further to vs our Saluation is moſt frée: But in reſpect of the<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 3.13 Eſai. 53.5.</note> price, it is the ful ſatiſfaction of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers iuſtice, and the valour is the bloud and death of our redéemer Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The end is that we being deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne <hi>(c)</hi> ſhould depart from iniquitie, and
<pb facs="tcp:226:80"/> dedicat our ſelues to the lord in newneſſe of life as chilldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> redemed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin &amp; death. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Regard w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare therefore, thy Chriſt hys death, yeeld not thy ſelf to ſathans ſnare, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for he that willingly<note n="(d)" place="margin">He. &amp; 10.26 27 Ro. 8.1.</note> by wilfull luſtes wil treade his death vnder his féete, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be partaker of his glory and lyfe.</p>
            <p>The third thing to obſerue is the alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which our Prophet vſeth in this place to the former propheſies, calling him the day ſpring, or as other the learned tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the word, a <hi>Braunch.</hi> For the former tranſlation great comfort is giuen therby to thée (deare reader) the word rightly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered in ſuch ſence as it ought, that is to vnderſtand by <hi>Oriens</hi> not the place wher the Sonne riſeth, but the Sonne himſelf, &amp; ſo doth <hi>Malachie</hi> vſe that metaphorical ſpech, when he calleth Chriſt<note n="a" place="margin">Mala. 4.2.</note> the ſonne of righteouſnes, vnder whoſe winges (or beames) lyeth health. Note heare our <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> alluding to this<note n="(b)" place="margin">Bucerus in Luk. 1</note> Scripture, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth Chriſt to be the trewe <hi>Meſsias,</hi> &amp; the ſame which was of them promiſed to bee the lord of life, by whom the church ſhuld haue her light &amp; full ſafety. Further looke into the Metaphor, the ſunne is the guide
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:226:80"/> of the world, the beawty of the Heauens, the light of the ſtarres and firmament: by him the vapours noyſome and peſtilent are taken from men, the ſpring, the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte, the times and ſeaſons haue their comfort and validitie of him. The Moone (the figure of Gods churche) hath her whole light of his light, of him depryued, ſhe is in her darkenes and eclipſed ſtate, by his preſence the night vaniſheth, the ſtormes and tempeſtuous tymes, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned, as barrennes turned into fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie, euery crooked occurrent vadeth, and all comfortes to men and creatures els,) preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. To aplie the ſame (with a thouſand more fruite,) thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt whenſoeuer thou ſaieſt this Pſalme, to thy heauenly Lorde the only begotten of God, the Sonne of righteouſnes which is the light<note n="(c)" place="margin">Io. 1. &amp; 8</note> of the world, the glory of<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 1.3</note> the father, the gouernour of al things, the way,<note n="e" place="margin">Io. 14.6</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth &amp; life it ſelf, to al that ſhal be ſaued, which by him ſelf redéemeth vs, with his fathers mercy clotheth vs, &amp; by his ſpirit regenerateth, ſanctifieth, &amp; guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs in him, to lyfe euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>The Sun entring the houſe euery dark corner is full of light, &amp; what filth remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,
<pb facs="tcp:226:81"/> is by him manifeſted: So where chriſt by faith appeareth in mans hart, all ignorance is baniſhed, and the light of his word reproueth all iniquitie, and driueth all error forth of mans ſoule. The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlateth the word not <hi>Oriens</hi> but <hi>Germen,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Beza in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notati. in Luc. c. 1.</note> and in his learned Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, geueth his reaſon vpon the nature of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrew word <hi>tſemach</hi> which, ſaith he, ſignifieth not <hi>Oriens,</hi> but <hi>germen</hi> a branch, &amp; he affirmeth there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet to allude vnto the wordes of Zacharie before,<note n="b" place="margin">Zach. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8 6.8 Iere. 23.5</note> and <hi>Ieremie</hi> which promiſed Chriſt to ſpring vp as out of the withered ſtocke of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted <hi>Dauid,</hi> of whom the world ſhould make ſmal accompt, but his groth ſhould be maruailous, &amp; therfore he addeth <hi>(from aboue)</hi> that ſo he may ſhew his comming vp to be contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plants of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. This is the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Dan. 2.44.</note> ſtone which commeth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mountaine without hands, &amp; doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt al the mountaines of the world, though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> builders refuſe him, he is chiefe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corner. This Chriſt is that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed branch which ſéemed<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſa. 53.2 Gal. 11.1.</note> withered &amp; beaten for his own ſinne, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of his fleſh he ſo viſited vs, that by his ſtripes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:226:81"/> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e made whole. This is the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Luc. 23.3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> gréene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>irident trée vpon whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cruell <hi>Jewes</hi> beſtowed their whole tirannie. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trée<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; vine of whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull branches receiue their light, &amp; knowledge, &amp; ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and power to paſſe the paſſage of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly peace. This is that branch by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s iudgement ſo eaten into the earth, as no b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dding or ſpring ſhuld be permitted him which by his owne power defendeth his owne cauſe againſt the Monarches of the world, &amp; yéeldeth foyle to the gates infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, &amp; ſpoyleth Satan of his pray. This is the Lord &amp; king of heauen &amp; earth to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the powers aboue, the ſpirits below, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n in earth, do ſtoupe &amp; fall before his throne, as to their only Lord and God, in whoſe hand is life and death. Now (deare reader) this branch is thine, geuen thée of God to be thy ſtaffe of defence in the day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f battel, and hath come himſelfe to viſite thy weake ſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; geue to thée his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aide. The Church of God ſhall dwell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt ſafely vnder the ſhadowe of this branche, for whoſoeuer ſtriueth againſt her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ſure to find him preſent in her, to whom he hath diſtended from aboue to
<pb facs="tcp:226:82"/> geue comfort to her miſeries which he c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth here <hi>darknes and the ſhadow of death,</hi> he that lifteth at her ſhall find her as<note n="(a)" place="margin">Zach. 12.3.</note> an heauie ſtone which ſhal cruſh them to péeces. Further note hee ſuffreth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his holy ones to be led into darke troubles and poyntes of death, but then is it his nature to viſite them: So hée came to <hi>Joſeph</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 39.20. &amp; 41.37. Pſal. 105.16 17.18.19.20 21.22.</note> in <hi>Pharaos</hi> chaynes. He ſuffred the Iſraelits to be driuen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Exo. 14.25.</note> brinke of the ſeas backſet with <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os</hi> whole power, but then he viſited them, gaue the light of life &amp; lead them in peace, the way of the troubleſome waters. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekia, Suſanna, Sydrach, Miſach,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bednego, Daniel, Jonas, Paule, Stephen,</hi> and many y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers ſince hath he by their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al brought forth Sathans power, &amp; ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in his deliuerie his ſecrete iudgements, and their weakenes not able to wound, or confound his inſtrumentes, which of them ſelues are of moſt féeble force. For neyther<note n="(d)" place="margin">2. Re. 18.30. ſtory Suſan Dan. 3.24.25. Dan. 6.22. Iona. 2.10 Act. 9.24. 2. Cor. 11.32</note> 
               <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> blaſphemie, the Prieſtes accuſation, the burning ouen, the Lions den, the Whalles bellie, <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> ire, or <hi>Saules</hi> furie, could cutte ſhorte his deare children of his preſence in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:226:82"/> middle of theſe their deathes but euen when their liues were thought (with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in <hi>Herods</hi> perſon) to be ſubiect to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death, then did the Lord beyond all expectation deliuer them.</p>
            <p>Finally to ſome ſuch as he beyond al time hath predeſtinate<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ephe. 1. Lions tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Lambes.</note> in time to be called, hath he appeared to their conciences and body, in the extreme darknes of their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in their ſhadowed hell, conſpiring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and his elect, and hath geuen them the light of his ſaluation, &amp; turned their raging race to warr w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his Church, into the moſt happie tracke of pacient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferings, and precious perſecution for his names ſake. Wherfore let vs pray for all perſecutors of his goſpel for neither we or yet themſelues do know whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath predeſtinate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to life. Did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles expect <hi>Pauls</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to their felowſhip, who was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt cruel enemie that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Romaine</hi> power &amp; the Phariſaicall <hi>Jewes</hi> ſent forth to their perſecution? &amp; did not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord lead this Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lie vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> féet (as it were) of thoſe holy la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes, euen then when he came w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> raging &amp; roaring<note n="(b)" place="margin">Act. 9. &amp;c.</note> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to deuour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous prince &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:226:83"/> moſt noble Monarch of the worlde, king Henry the Eyght, purpoſe to foſter the Lordes people in Englande, when he ſat himſelfe<note n="(b)" place="margin">Fox. Act.</note> in iudgement, agaynſt the Godly Martir of Chriſt <hi>Lamhert,</hi> and yet dyd the Lorde viſit his Princely harte ſo, that by the light of his Chriſt, (the ſpirite of God opening his harte) he was made the Lordes inſtrument, vtterly to thruſt out that horrible Pope, wyth all his pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, which no king before him could bring to paſſe, albeit they eftſoones attempted, ſundry times to cut him ſhort. Which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth Gods good lyke of his miniſtery, &amp; with him, of all ſuch Biſhops and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as did by doctrine ſtirre vp his hart her to themſelues, or moſt of them before, being ſworne to the Romiſhe obedience. The noble Father and Martir of Chriſt, M. <hi>Cranmer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. Cranmer Archbi. of Cant. ſome time an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> late the Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, ſhall we not accompt him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the lawfull miniſters of God? a truſt none will be ſo wilfull as once to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inke him vnworthie, moſt reuerence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Catalogie of Gods true and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miniſters, in his time. And yet my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bretherne in his perſno and actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> found apparant, ſuch <hi>(a)</hi> blemiſhes,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:226:83"/> as for the ſame, all of his lyke inſtitution are of ſome vouched vmméete for the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the Church of God. I ſpeake not this to iniurie the fame of that holy man, whom the heauens haue receiued, but to offer ſuch comfort to others, as I haue (I truſt rightly) receiued my ſelfe:<note place="margin">Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor from Idolatry, to the goſpell.</note> being in the dayes of Quéene Mary, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vp in Popery, and made an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Prieſt, often committing moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſacrileage to God, by the ſacrifiſing that Idolatrous Cake and counterfeyted Chriſt, to God the Father, againſt the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt his ſonne. But I dayly praiſe the Lord my God, who hath taken mercy vpon me, and called me from that power of darknes, and hath tranſlated me vnto the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Col. 1.13.</note> kingdome of his dear ſonne Ieſus, and of &amp; from an Idolatrous Prieſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorantly caryed into error, hath choſen me wyth many others my Godly Bretherne, to be a faythfull miniſter and true Preacher of his holy Goſpell, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I craue for reſtes to the world, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which haue taſted of the ſwéet gyltes of his holy ſpirite, by his merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and riche goodneſſe, powred into
<pb facs="tcp:226:84"/> their harts, by my miniſtrie though a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But through chriſt called by grace to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of the word of truth, through whoſe good gifts, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> portion of his ſacred ſpirit, giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me for their good, and my continual comfort, they are to confeſſe his grace apparant in my miniſtry, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> others our godly brethren called to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office. This I ſay not boſtingly after the fleſhe, but witneſſing, Gods great graces in me (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the leaſt) after his calling me, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many others from idolatry to his ſeruice: And not to yéeld my ſelf, &amp; ſuch like whoſe hartes be truly turned to the Lord, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribe to ſuch ſharp cenſure as paſſeth to the offence of many a ſoule. But <hi>Saul</hi> as he is not aſhamed to<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.11 12.13.14.15 16.17.</note> confeſſe his error &amp; blaſphemies: So being by the Lorde in mercy changed to <hi>Paule,</hi> warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth vs (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him) good courage &amp; comfort to procede in our offices: &amp; daring to ſay of himſelf (erſt a perſecuter) as of his fellow miniſters which neuer were ſuch, ſéeing<note n="(c)" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.1</note> we haue this miniſtery &amp;c. He doth hereby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more embolden vs, with humblenes of hart to chalenge the like authority, to preach &amp; to adminiſter the ſacraments of the lord, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> and aſwel as ſuch others our brethren by
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:226:84"/> the ſingular grace of god, either preſerued from ſuch idolatry, or ſince that time cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the function eccleſiaſticall. Theſe ſpéeches therfore, <hi>Q. Maries</hi> prieſtes, <hi>K. Henries</hi> prieſtes,<note place="margin">Indecent ſpeaches a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie</note> &amp;c. are not ſo warely ſet downe, as becommeth the place of ſuch which ſéeme ſufficient to ſupply y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wants of this eccleſiaſticall gouernment. But the lord aſſiſt in his mercy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate preſent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his holy ſpirit, &amp; grant to this our migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty monarch, a zelous ſpirite in him, yet more &amp; more to remoue &amp; reteine, as the worde of God, the honor of this his holy church in England, &amp; the condition of our age &amp; time, ſhall approue for truth moſt conuenient. The places of <hi>Joſias</hi> and <hi>EZe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi> are not to beat vs down,<note place="margin">Their allea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> or to bear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary opinion, from lacke in my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Omitting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priuat example, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ioſias,</hi> which can not in good diuinitie be drawne to a publique commandement, I will onely note of the other place, which ſéemeth to ſundrye, to ſtande for a law preceptorie, as well to vs now, as to the Leuits then. Firſt I ſay, that Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie is an horrible ſin, but not eſtranged is the Idolater from grace, if the Lorde vouchſafe him<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eze. 18.22 23. Eze. 44.10.</note> repentance. And where
<pb facs="tcp:226:85"/> as the Lord there cutteth thoſe Leuits fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Alter at Ieruſalem, and the office of the Prieſt, which fell to Idolatry, he doth not ſay, &amp; this ſhall be a perpetuall lawe to my houſe &amp; Church for euer: Neyther did the Leuits alwais, ſo deale to fore, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Moiſes</hi> law. Did not <hi>Aaron,</hi> fal to Idolatrie, when he made<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 32.1.</note> with a gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen toole the molten image, &amp; proclaimed a ſolempne feaſt day therfore? attributing that ſelfe Idolatrous worſhip to the lord, &amp; made an Aulter before the Idoll, and if wel we weigh whoſe office it was in that congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to offer vp ſacrifice, we ſhall further touch <hi>Aaron</hi> his perſon, as alſo <hi>Moiſes</hi> ſéemeth to lay the whole crime vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.<note place="margin">Aaron not remoued from the prieſthood notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding his great ſinne in Idolatry.</note> Yet behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great mercy of God in the time of the law. Nor is <hi>Aaron</hi> by god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, or by his magiſtrate <hi>Moiſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priued of his dignitie, remoued from his miniſtery, nor ſlaine with the ſlaughter of the ſword at <hi>Moiſes</hi> his hands, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>.3000.</hi> of the Iſralits were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlaine for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame horrible &amp; Idolatrous fact. This example may not moue ſuch whom it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne to boldnes of ſinne, neither is the place of <hi>EZech.</hi> written to tye al times to that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall law. But ſo hath gods wiſdome
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:226:85"/> enriched his written ſcriptures with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in ſeuerity &amp; mercy in his chriſt, that ſin may be condemned, &amp; the penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner find fauor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God.<note place="margin">Ez. 44.10.</note> It might be aſked whether all the whole Chapter be of like authoritie, or onely that part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Leuits? if all, then further mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter is to be conſidered, then either would be liked of many, or tollerated of any true chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the church of god. If only that remaine, touching the fallen Leuits, and not that in the <hi>.9.</hi> verſe. <hi>17.18.22.</hi> &amp;c. For gods cauſe, ſhew vs ſome priueleadge, for that mater only from the reſt. But deare bretherne, the whole chapter conſidered, ſendeth vs to the ſame mind that erſt we were of, that is, that this law was to the Iewiſh prieſthod, &amp; not to vs: &amp; the ſhrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſubſcribing hands of men moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in the miniſtery rightly meaſured with the aboundant gifts of gods ſpirite, to them, after repentance giuen of god, to ſeale his good like of their elected place, &amp; continuance in the function of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, aſwel to his Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> as to ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry his excelent diſciples in our, times gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not a little comfort to thoſe in that
<pb facs="tcp:226:86"/> predicament, notwithſtanding the ſeuere cenſure of ſundry zealous and learned perſons. I purpoſe not at all to fauour ſuch popiſh Maſſe prieſtes, whoſe hartes remayning without Religion, haue and doe frame themſelues to euery chaunge, thereby to ſatiſfy their lucring luſt: for theſe béeing onely <hi>Temporarii,</hi> are not in any ſort tollerable in the holy miniſterie of Chriſtes worde and ſacraments: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet to ſupport ſuch <hi>Queene Maries</hi> prieſtes, as béeinge in her darcke raigne admitted by that Popiſhe ennoyling, do yet with the former, couer their nowe Idolatrous hartes, with the mantell of externe obedience. But if ſo it be, that God in his great mercy haue fully alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and to him ſelfe by him ſelfe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the hartes of ſome of theſe, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Perſons as extraordynarily, (which may be perceiued by his giftes and Spirite in them,) then I ſée not, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their publique confeſſion, and time of tryall, (which were very neceſſary) why eyther the Church ſhould refuſe to readmitte them to the miniſterie of the Goſpell, or any the children ſhould
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:226:86"/> impugne ſuch their godly Mothers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte. For this cauſe was<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.16</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> receyued to mercy, that Ieſus Chriſte ſhould firſte ſhewe vppon him all longe ſufferinge, to the example of them, which in time to come ſhould beléeue in Chriſt, to eternall lyfe. This mercy, note (good Reader) is not ended, when <hi>Paule</hi> is thereby receyued to grace, but it contynueth (and that for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable example) admittinge that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Conuerte, to the preaching of the Goſpell. And as the Goſpell yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth grace to this our conuert: So the law is not altogether voyd of fauour the ſlyding Prieſte <hi>Aaron,</hi> as before. Neyther yet doe I ſpeake to confyrme the generall Troupe of the Idolatrous prieſtes admitted, eſpecially ſithe they haue not turned to the LORDE, vntill the mighty God hath taken from them their vaine truſt, and placed againe hys trewe Religion, which Prieſtes haue continewed till the day by Lawe ſet, in their maſſinge, and wiſhe the ſame yet in harte, in the middle of theyr miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:226:87"/> theſe whereſoeuer they be, I doe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſo they are and cannot by law as yet be remoued. But I only ſet downe my diſlike of this opinion, that if once a Quéene <hi>Maries</hi> prieſt, or King <hi>Henries</hi> and Kyng <hi>Edwardes</hi> Prieſt (ſo they bée termed) then can they not in any caſe, how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer beautified with ſpiritual giftes, or conuerted in conſcience, be admitted to the function of the eccleſiaſticall miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. As I willingly confeſſe that ther may becauſe of diſtruſt into the moſt of ſuch: So yet I cannot achieue the ſight of this, that from all ſuch the grace of God is ſo farre ſhortened. If through repentance by his holy ſpirite they be purely ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and accompted in Gods ſight for his ſonne Chriſt, in whom they beleue, as if they had remained innocent: Why ſhuld the ſeueritie of men in earth ſhut from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſterie in his Church, thoſe whom his mercy from the heauens hath receiued as moſt deare to himſelfe? Or yet from the paſtorall office ſuch perſons as the Lord accompteth innocent? But it may bée ſayd the Church is offended at them, they therfore cannot profite the congregation.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:226:87"/> I ſay, the godly in the church doe reſpect the goſpell, which the man bringeth, and not the man his meſſenger, neither ſhall the wicked reprobate<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.19 Iude. 4</note> be holpen by the pureſt miniſter, or yet the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tton be hindered or want their promiſed commoditie in the weakeſt paſtor. Could the Iſraelites be ignorant of <hi>Aarons</hi> fal? or the Apoſtles and Church then of <hi>Peters</hi> deniall in the iudgement hall, or his eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones infirmitie<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> at <hi>Antioch?</hi> Whoſe crimes were not ſmall, yet was not the one or the other for the offence of the Church through their fall, abandoned the miniſterie. Theſe things by occaſion thus touched for thy taſt and ſtay of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I haſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of theſe my labours, with this laſt obſeruation to whom it may con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerne. Chriſt is giuen of God his father to geue light to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſit in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> darknes of error &amp; ſinne, &amp; to guide their wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring ſteps &amp; wide walking féete, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, which is the way of peace. Now is the time wherein moſt amplie this his office is by his grace executed in this nation, &amp; yet are there many which hauing in the darknes of the late perſecution, ſéene and
<pb facs="tcp:226:88"/> receiued great light of the Goſpell, are now in cleare ſhine of the ſame, either with the Moules digging and dwelling in earthly things, and couet the darknes of Mammon, reſeruing to Chriſt and his word their lippes alone: Or els with <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> that <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> when they ſhould ſeale vp the fulnes of their ioye in receiuing their ſaluation ſent, and obeying his king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome preſent, they as men all wearied of eternal life, ſhut vp their harts from the Lord therof, reiect his goſpell, reſuſe their former fayth, and returne to the vomite of poperie erſt caſt from them. To all ſuch Chriſt is a ſtumbling ſtone, a ſtone of offence, but in déede to them he is a ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible iudge to pronounce the end due to their <hi>Apostaſie</hi> ſo relapſed:<note place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 10. 2. Pet. 2.20.21.22.</note> hell and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting damnation. The lord in his great mercie kéepe vs from this fall, and geue vs to apprehend his Chriſt our light and leader, that we may dayly walke in his ſhining law, by the conduction of his ho-ſpirite, vntill we attaine the fruition of his eternall peace. To whom with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy ghoſt, thrée perſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, one &amp; our eternall God, be al glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd power for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:226:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
